<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jack's Digital Workbench - Autism</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/feeds/autism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jackdewinter.github.io/</id><updated>2021-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Autism and Patience Do Not Mix</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2021/07/12/autism-and-patience-do-not-mix/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2021-07-12:/2021/07/12/autism-and-patience-do-not-mix/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past week has been one of the longest weeks that I can remember
in a long time.  To be blunt, I have been sick for almost the entire
week.  And while I am feeling better, I have to acknowledge that my
patience is almost at a breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past week has been one of the longest weeks that I can remember
in a long time.  To be blunt, I have been sick for almost the entire
week.  And while I am feeling better, I have to acknowledge that my
patience is almost at a breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain: I hate being sick.  While I usually take good care of
myself and take breaks and relax when I need to, I do like to keep busy.
[more]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend was not so different than any other.  We were having some
work done on the house scheduled for the following Wednesday, and those
contractors needed the electrical outlets removed so that they could do
their job.
After talking with my father-in-law, who is a licensed electrician, I
went with the plan that we worked out together and within two hours,
the required work was done.  Working in a relatively hot attic, I was
able to disconnect the required electrical circuits and leave them
safe, all to plan. I double checked with my father-in-law on what I did
and gave him an &amp;ldquo;after action report&amp;rdquo; that he agreed with, and everything
was good.  Knowing I &amp;ldquo;did well&amp;rdquo; according to my father-in-law, I started
working on my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2021/07/12/markdown-linter-full-of-sound-and-fury/"&gt;PyMarkdown project&lt;/a&gt;
and got a lot done.  That was possible because it was the Fourth of July,
and as I had Monday off, and I knew that I could write the entire article on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Monday arrived rather slowly.  I woke up with a headache that just wouldn&amp;rsquo;t
go away, and a lethargy that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shake.  I started writing the
article and got it mostly completed, but each paragraph that I put
into that article seemed twice as hard as the one before it.  By the time four o-clock
rolled around, I just knew that I was going to miss my usual Monday 11:59 PM
deadline.  I will spare you the details of how it progressed except to say
that it landed me in the local Emergency Room at 10:00 PM that evening.
Being sent home after five hours, the only thing the doctor and I could
figure out that there was something in the attic that got into my system and
made me react to it.  Whether it was the heat or some old insulation
didn&amp;rsquo;t matter, I reacted to it in a bad way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday morning I called into work, letting them know what happened and
that I needed an extra day to try and get better.  Wednesday arrived and
I completed my work for the day, but not without a decent nap in the middle
of the day and another nap after work.  Thursday was better in that I did not need the
afternoon nap, but it was Friday before I needed no nap.  But after
completing work each day, I literally did not do any of the things that
I would normaly do in the evening.  Today, Saturday, is the first day since
Sunday that I have been able to do anything on the computer that was not
work related.  And it really has been taxing my patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, part of my Autism diagnosis is anxiety related.  The best way to
explain my anxiety disorder is that my mind starts to evaluate the different
scenarios that can occur, taking up more and more bandwidth in my brain until
I am overwhelmed.  Depending on who and what is involved in any scenario,
I can often prune some of those scenarios as being unrealistic or unlikely.
But without a neurotypical person&amp;rsquo;s point of view, any pruning that is related
to social circumstances or another person&amp;rsquo;s emotional states is severely
limited.  And that is where the anxiety builds more and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help address that anxiety, I have found two patterns that usually work
very well together: overcommunication and consistency.  If I am working
with you, I will probably tell you something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, I have Autism and I tend to overcommunicate.  If it gets to be too
much, please work with me to help us find a good level of communication.
I am also open, honest, and straight forward, so please let me know
if I say something wrong, as it is probably an oversight on my part.
I know I am probably going to miss something, and I hope you will
work with me to get it out in the open, dealt with it, and move on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, that is the overcommunication in a nutshell.  Most of the time,
people ask questions they have, and we have a good conversation about
communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consistency is the other part of my coping mechanism.  I do not
feel the need to be as rigid as others with Autism, but I still
need structure.  I try and plan out the following day before I go to
bed, just getting a high level point of view on what I need to do the
next day.  For work days, that usually means a block of &amp;ldquo;work&amp;rdquo;
followed by walking our dog Bruce, taking a shower, relaxing for an
hour watching something, making dinner, and then some work in the evening
on a project.  For a non-work day, that usually means some work on a project
until noon, doing work around the house or spending time with my wife in
the afternoon, and then following a similar evening pattern to a work day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds obsessive, it is not meant to be.  Based on the amount of
analysis that my mind constantly does, that planning strives to quiet
some of those analytics down.  Unless there is a good reason not to, I know
I am going to walk Bruce every day.  I do not need to analyze it that much.
If anything, it relaxes me to know that it is a constant and that me and
Bruce will have a good two mile walk together every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is where my lack of patience and this week have collided with
each other like two freight trains on a single track.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the communication
front, if I usually think with the bandwidth of a six-lane highway, I
was probably thinking like I was done to only one lane, and there was
construction being performed on that lane.  On the consistency front,
my entire schedule was destroyed and replaced with a &amp;ldquo;whatever I have
the energy for&amp;rdquo; schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[more]&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry><entry><title>Anxiety</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2021/04/25/anxiety/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2021-04-25:/2021/04/25/anxiety/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Will anyone read my articles?  Will anyone understand what I am trying to say with those
articles?  What will people think when they read my articles?  These are normal feelings
for a normal person to feel when they write an article.  Did I say the right things?  Did
I talk …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Will anyone read my articles?  Will anyone understand what I am trying to say with those
articles?  What will people think when they read my articles?  These are normal feelings
for a normal person to feel when they write an article.  Did I say the right things?  Did
I talk too much or too little?  Did they laugh at what I said because they thought I was
&amp;ldquo;ha-ha&amp;rdquo; funny or &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; funny?  Those are normal feelings for a normal person to feel
when they have a conversation with someone else.  Do I contribute my share to
my team at work?  Do I help my team work more efficiently, or am I
constantly slowing them down?  When my team needs me, am I there to help?  Those are
normal feelings for a normal person to feel about their workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine writing those articles with barely any intuitive understanding of how
people may respond, only that understanding gained from hard fought experience.  Visualize
trying to have a conversation without having any decent grasp on the social cues that
most people use to guide their conversations in the right direction.  Consider the
difficulties others have in trying to navigate the meandering stream that is your team,
your workplace, your culture.  Try thinking about these three difficulties overlapping
and happening at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is an oversimplification of how people with Autism feel a lot of the time. However,
I feel that those descriptions start to encompass the difficulties that I face every day.
Trying to talk to others about how you think and feel is a daunting task for anyone.  But
add another level of difficulty on to that conversation because you know that you think
differently than most people.  That is why a lot of people with Autism, people that
want to try and fit in, choose not to disclose their Autism to those around them.
I guess most of the time people decide the pain of hiding who they truly are is less
painful than talking about how different they are than others.  I know I kept on
making that exact decision for myself for years before I decided no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the personal decision not to disclose often causes negative consequences down the line.
As this article from
&lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/autism/autism-and-the-workforce"&gt;Psychology Today&lt;/a&gt;
states, 20 percent of people are unemployed and only 58 percent of people that are adults
under 25 work for pay.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time I have heard numbers like these. And,
as the article states, other estimates are much higher.  But
those percentages sound reasonable to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture yourself as being a person with Autism, sitting in an interview room.  You
try to form that bond with the hiring manager, even though it is hard for you to
establish connections with other people.  In addition, its incredibly difficult to
look your interviewer in the eye when talking, which makes things worse.  Even if you
make it through the emotionally jarring interview
process, you know that you are going to be constantly trying to understand the social
dynamics of that new workplace.  That is a tiring job for someone with Autism, whether
that person is successful or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you find the courage to decide to disclose to others that you have Autism, many of
those problems do not go away.  If the interviewer does not understand Autism, they might
evaluate your interview like a normal person.  That never goes well.  While I don&amp;rsquo;t
blame them, quite a few of my interviews have ended with a polite &amp;ldquo;we think you are a
technical fit, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think you fit into our company culture&amp;rdquo;.  And hopefully your
hiring manager is present at a successful interview so you can also interview them.  If
not, you may end up in a situation where you don&amp;rsquo;t know how your immediate supervisor
will react to your Autism.  Even worse, you meet the hiring manager and they soon get
reorganized within your company, with you working for someone who couldn&amp;rsquo;t care
less about you having Autism.  That sucks.  Been there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are incredibly lucky, like I have been in my last couple of jobs, your team&amp;rsquo;s
management understands that you are different, but they need your help to be educated on
how &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; are different.  From personal
experience, this is a good position to be in.  But even in that position, I worry that I
take up too much of their time with things that they consider to be trivial.  You see, I
do not intuitively know what is trivial to them, just what I have observed and learned
from past conversations with them.  Rarely is there any intuitive component to learning
from these conversations, so I have had many conversations with people that started with words like
&amp;ldquo;I remember you said&amp;rdquo;, had words like &amp;ldquo;I interpreted that to mean&amp;rdquo; in the middle, and
words like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll try and understand better next time&amp;rdquo; at the end.  I do understand that
happens to everyone, but I have no clue on what a good or bad level of that happening is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even those things are not the worst parts of how it feels like to be someone with
Autism.  For a lot of people with Autism, there is the anxiety.  For me, that anxiety
is fueled by my ability to analyze.  In each of the situations I have outlined so far,
my mind is racing, trying to analyze each of those possible outcomes and trying to select
the best outcome based on limited information.  If I am lucky enough to have found a
pattern that helps me avoid analyzing some of those outcomes, that pruning is almost
always based on previous experiences and my understand of those experiences. That means
that I often make bad choices based on bad experiences or an incomplete understanding of
those experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know someone with Autism that is doing better than average, chances are they can
mitigate some of the issues that come with Autism with some of the positive
aspects of Autism.  For myself, while my seemingly never sending stream of analysis can
be paralyzing, it can also be very useful.  In my professional job as a Software
Development Engineer in Test (or SDET for short),
being able to analyze the applications that I write test automation for is a very big
asset.  Without spending too much energy, I can quickly digest either source code or
documentation for a project and understand it without too much effort.  As I go, I form
a list of questions that help me clarify my understanding, sometimes down to a very fine
degree of understanding.  Using all that information together, I can quickly generate an
analysis of that project&amp;rsquo;s strengths and weaknesses, providing risk/impact/benefit
assessments.  I can then take those assessments and generate a solid plan on how to
mitigate those tests with manual testing and test automation, providing ideas on how
to measure the efficiency and coverage of those tests to my management.  All this
good stuff comes from my ability to analyze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I believe that I do a great job and that job contains many tasks that I am very
well suited to executing.  But it is also something I cannot turn off.  I can lose myself
temporarily in things like my writing, my music, and my movies.  But when those are not
there, my mind starts swirling again trying to analyze everything around me.  And it is
not only the current things that my mind analyzes, but things that have occurred in the
past couple of weeks.  I will be out walking our dog when I start to think about all
sorts of things, unable to just enjoy walking our dog.  To be clear, it is not our dog&amp;rsquo;s
fault that I don&amp;rsquo;t always enjoy our walks, it is mine. I just cannot stop my mind from
racing around like a hamster on drugs trying to run a four-minute mile in three minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does all of this relate to anxiety?  For me, as those different scenarios are
playing out in real life, my mind is racing to analyze that stream of data as I am living
through it.  Sometimes it feels like I continuously have a set of sports announcers in my
head giving me a critique, questioning every word that I uttered and every expression and
micro-expression that I emoted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was I looking at the right places during the
conversation?  Did I maintain enough eye contact, or should I add some more in for good
measure?  Did I now just add to much eye contact, so I am staring at them like a creep?
Ooh, they are wearing a nice piece of jewelry that sparkles.  Crap, I looked at the bright
shiny thing instead of where I should be looking.  Did they notice?  Even worse, did they
notice that I looked there and think I am checking them out?  They just crossed their
arms. What does that mean for them? If I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it means for them, what does it
mean for most people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That level of noise coming from your own brain is hard to drown out.  As we are all
influenced by what we are experiencing, that noise becomes part of the data that I use to
shape my conversations and actions.  And because my experiences are incomplete and that
clatter is not always trustworthy, I have lots of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the tools that a lot
of other people have at their disposal to answer those questions, I am then left with the
bulk of those questions left unanswered.  To make things worse, if I reach out to others
to try and answer those questions, I am not sure which of those questions it is socially
acceptable to ask people.  There is no &amp;ldquo;one level&amp;rdquo;, just the various levels of friendship
or professionalism that they have in their interactions with me. It is frustrating and
induces more anxiety.  And that adds more anxiety back into the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as with most things in life, I have a choice.  I can give up, I can fight to
maintain, or I can fight to overcome.  Every day when I wake up, and many times during
the day, I can choose one of those three positions with respect to my anxiety.  I can
leverage my love for music to help me drown out most of the analysis noise, leaving me
with the useful analysis that helps me do my job properly.  I can provide myself a well
contained environment that is healthy but static, so that I don&amp;rsquo;t try and analyze the
movement and behavior of things as they pass through my workspace.  I can take the
proactive step of learning how to breath properly and meditate.  While I never get into
a meditative state, it does help me find some manner of inner peace.  Each little bit
helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As to those questions at the start of the article?  I have a close group of friends and
family whose opinions I trust.  I don&amp;rsquo;t have to make my articles work for everyone; I just
need to focus on getting my message across to that small group of people.  By narrowing my
focus, it helps me drown out some of that noise.  On conversing with others, if I am
engaging with someone frequently, I usually warn them that I have Autism and can (and
will) talk for hours.  Most people are understanding, and after the usual bit of
apprehension, realize that I am just trying to find something to talk to them about to
make them smile or laugh.  Often times they know someone with some form of Autism and
they will then ask for some help in relating to that person.  With respect to my team at work,
I just make sure to overcommunicate and use reflective
communication to ensure that I am understanding things properly.  And yes, I use the
I-phrases like &amp;ldquo;what I heard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;what I understand&amp;rdquo;.  After all, I am asking for their
help, not accusing them of doing something wrong.  In a fair world, we would both
work equally on that communication.  But the world is not fair, so I need to be the
one to focus on how I communicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why every day I choose to wake up and be as positive as I can be. Even on the
bad days where I seem to feel the weight of the world on my shoulders. I can either let
that anxiety drag me down, or I can be positive and try and make a positive impact on the
world and the people around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, if I don&amp;rsquo;t push back against my own anxiety, no one else will.  It&amp;rsquo;s all up to
me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry><entry><title>Autism And Dementia</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2021/02/28/autism-and-dementia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-28T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2021-02-28:/2021/02/28/autism-and-dementia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I started writing these articles, I intended to write one article every month to
help people with and without Autism understand what goes on in my mind.  By exposing how
my Autism affects me, my hope is that each reader will be able to apply some small portion
of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I started writing these articles, I intended to write one article every month to
help people with and without Autism understand what goes on in my mind.  By exposing how
my Autism affects me, my hope is that each reader will be able to apply some small portion
of what they read in these articles.  Every person with Autism manifests their Autism
differently from everyone else.  As such, having a goal of helping everyone with any
connection to Autism would be a tough goal to achieve.  My more modest goal is that each
article will have some impact on at least one person&amp;rsquo;s life.  Maybe it helps someone to
understand a loved one, it encourages someone to be a little kinder to someone with Autism
in their life, or it causes someone to take a minute to read the article and then think
about it. That is why I write these articles, to ignite that spark in my readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, that is how I was raised.  I have a great mother who raised three children on
her own starting in the late 1970s - a time where a decision like that was not very
popular.  Over the years, we have talked about the reasons why she did that, and her
response always remained the same: &amp;ldquo;I love you kids, and I knew it
would be hard, but I also knew that I could do it.  So, I did it.&amp;rdquo;  From there, it was
always a solid talk about how her faith in God, as a Roman Catholic, helped her in the
tough times.  There is always a mention of how we often threw roadblocks in her way,
which all three of us blush or laugh at when they are now mentioned.
Outshining all of that, was the firm statement from my mother that, through it
all, her love for us never faltered. And in return, all us kids had one extra best friend
in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were not the only ones that she affected.  By continuing to be involved in her
church, she was fortunate enough to meet, fall in love with, and marry her second
husband, Gerry.  She loved Gerry&amp;rsquo;s kids as her own, often speaking of his kids and his
grandkids with the same love that she has for her own
grandkids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving back was so wired into her system, that she found a job working
with the Red Cross to provide aide to the elderly, by helping them with everyday things
that they could no longer do.  When we heard stories of the people she helped,
it would be easy to believe that those people were related to our family by
the way my mother talked about them.  Not one to be idle, in her off hours it was rare
that she was not sitting in her favorite chair sewing or knitting.  She used those skills
to make doll clothes for children in need, and baby blankets for newborns at the local
hospital.  Once again, when I asked, she would say that
it kept her busy and that she was giving back to a community that had helped her when
she needed it.  So, she did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is because of this, that I have started writing these articles and writing in general.
As someone with Autism, I cannot help everyone out there, but perhaps I can help get some
manner of message to some of the people that need it and do my bit to help.  Write the
next great
science fiction novel?  Tried that and failed miserably.  Invent some new software that
will revolutionize the way we do something?  Tried that and did decently okay back in the
1990s.  Write from my heart about how my Autism affects me?  To echo what my mother said
with my own spin: &amp;ldquo;It isn&amp;rsquo;t going to be easy, and I know being vulnerable is hard, but
I know I can do it.  So, I did it.&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that bedrock of my life, my mother, is now faltering.  After 75+ years of her life,
my mother is being attacked by the disease known as dementia.  Its effects are brutal.
There was a time when I could pick up the phone and have a good 30-minute conversation
with one of my best friends, now we struggle to have a 30 second conversation that is
coherent.  In the past, we used to laugh at all the stupid things I did as a kid,
now, I try to hold back the tears as I tell my brother and sister about the calls I
have had with my mom.  Instead of talking about our next family gathering with
Mom and all three sibilings, we end up talking about funeral plans and how
we know she is in pain while she is losing her mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last decent conversation I remember having with my mother is in August, right after
my son&amp;rsquo;s birthday.  It was a bit sketchy in places, and it was obvious that some of her
long-term memory was going, but it was a good conversation.  Every two or three weeks
after that, some element of the conversation dropped away.  It was as if someone was taking
the color out of my mother&amp;rsquo;s life bit-by-bit, and the struggle in her voice to form
sentences was obvious.  After that, it was harder to call her.  I knew that when I called,
it would hang over me like a dark cloud for the next couple of days.  I started making
excuses as to why I could not call her, convincing myself it was for the better.  I was
just scared.  I was losing my best friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This really hit home just after New Year&amp;rsquo;s Day when I called her to wish her a happy
new year.  I wish I could relate to you what that conversation was about, but I honestly
do not have a clue about it myself.  I asked her how she was doing, and she said she was
sad.  And then she mentioned something about children and red and a couple of other things
I could not understand.  Talking with my sister later, she mentioned that she must be
having a good day that I was able to get 1 or 2 coherent minutes out of her.  Most days, my
sister was struggling with her to even get that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That really threw me.  I tried writing an article about Autism after that call, but
nothing came out.  Every time I started to write, I wrote one sentence and stared at the
screen for 15 minutes before giving up.  In each case, I always went back to thinking
about Mom and her dementia.  After a good solid six weeks of repeating that process and
getting nowhere, I had a &amp;ldquo;lightbulb&amp;rdquo; moment.  It was then, that I realized that this was
also affecting me on another level, a more personal level.  I was afraid for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autism by itself is no walk in the park.  Sure, I have learned to mitigate a lot of it,
but it still a lot of work.  I was lucky to find a second wife later in life, who takes
the time to understand me.  In return, she reasonably asks me to understand her quirks
and accept her for who she is.  Our conversations often reminds me of my conversations
with my mother as I was growing up, trying to figure things out.  Now, instead of being
able to share my happiness with my mother, I see how quickly my mother&amp;rsquo;s dementia is
removing most of the woman that I knew, admired, and loved.  That&amp;rsquo;s chilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, as someone with Autism, I have spent my life working on my communication skills
and overcoming a lack of social skills by using the positive aspects of my Autism to
compensate.  Back in August, when my mother&amp;rsquo;s dementia was getting worse, I looked up
the definition of dementia on the
&lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013"&gt;Mayo Clinic&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;,
and it looked like it was tailor made as a nasty list for people with Autism.  In the
Cognitive part of the list, it talks about “difficulty” items. Most people with Autism
struggle with all/some of these “difficulty” items and, if they are lucky, can find ways
to compensate for all/some of those items.  The thought of losing some of my ability
to mitigate my Autism sucks.  The &lt;em&gt;Psychological Changes&lt;/em&gt; part of the list is not much
better.  To be truthful, I know that my Autism has caused me to experience at least
4 out of the 7 things on that list in some form.  It is only by working hard and trusting
in my doctor, my psychologist, and my friends that I now keep their influence down to a
bare minimum.  But if they get worse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, part of having Autism is being hyper-aware of things around me.  It is hard to
miss things when you brain is busy analyzing things for most of your life.  At 52
years of age, I am noticing that I am forgetting some little things here and there, mostly
short-term stuff.  There are times where I have difficulty in finding the right words to
communicate something, only for the word that I am looking for to be something simple.
And as funny as it sounds, I am forgetting where I placed my keys more often these days,
something that almost never happened in the past.  And with what my mother is going
through, I sometimes wonder if I am getting some early tinges of dementia, or if this
is just normal&amp;hellip; or at least as normal as a person with Autism can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am not one to wallow, I am one to get out there and do stuff.  I know I get knocked
down from time to time, but I also know that I am not alone.  My family, in their own
unique ways, helps to give me the courage to dust myself off and stand up again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I worried about my mother?  Yes.  But the only thing I can do there is to try and call
her to let her know I am here, and to send peaceful thoughts her way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I still worried that the same thing that is afflicting my mother will one day afflict
me?  Yes.  But I hopefully have some time before that happens, I can look for positive
actions that I can do to help me combat this disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does my writing help me as much as it helps others?  Yes.  For me, I think that my
writing helps me as much as others by acting like my own
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging"&gt;rubber duck&lt;/a&gt;.
It hurts to talk about things sometimes, but if I can help one person in some way, it
is good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry><entry><title>Autism And How It Affects My View of Christmas</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2020/12/20/autism-and-how-it-affects-my-view-of-christmas/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2020-12-20:/2020/12/20/autism-and-how-it-affects-my-view-of-christmas/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people in my life have been very understanding, but as always, there are a decent
number of people that have left some lasting negative impacts.  Some of those people I
blame for their actions, and some of those people were just reacting to me and how
my Autism appeared …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people in my life have been very understanding, but as always, there are a decent
number of people that have left some lasting negative impacts.  Some of those people I
blame for their actions, and some of those people were just reacting to me and how
my Autism appeared to them.  But equally important to how I appeared to them was my
Autism and how it has affected my view of Christmas throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say that I was diagnosed with Autism in my 40s, that does not mean that I did not
have Autism before that.  It just means instead of &amp;ldquo;the weird guy with Autism&amp;rdquo;, I was
just the &amp;ldquo;the weird guy&amp;rdquo;.  And back when I was a kid, I definitely was &amp;ldquo;the weird kid&amp;rdquo;.
Contrary to the modern definition of Autism, the definition of Autism when I was a kid
was someone with below-average intellect who had severe problems interacting with the
world.  I did not have the benefit of any helpful labels and programs to help me
succeed, such as the help that my son was able to get throughout his childhood.  It was
just me trying to figure things out as I went, often feeling alone and alien, wanting
to fit in with my peers, but not knowing how to even start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is where my negative view of Christmas started, based on a strong dislike of what
I perceived to be the over-commercialization of Christmas.  As I have been trying to
understand myself better over the years, it has been hard for me to disentangle two
aspects of this dislike from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
original reason that I disliked Christmas was indeed a selfish one: our family did not
have enough growing up.  My mom is one of the most important people in my life, and
each year I saw her struggle throughout the year to make sure we had our basic
necessities and whatever other reasonable things she could get for us.  It pissed me
off that my father was almost never in the picture.  The thought of my mother having
to ask our local church or food bank for help and for presents, either made me feel
embarrassed and mad at the same time.  With the kind heart that I know my mother has,
I am pretty confident
that she felt like she should have been a better mother, even though that was not in
the cards. For me, even though my mom did everything for us out love for us,
Christmas was a time when I always felt more negative emotions that positive ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is where the second aspect kicks in: my peers.  I remember the feeling of
dread that preceded going back to school after Christmas break.  Each year, I would go
back to school and everyone in the class
would be bragging about the wonderful things they got for Christmas.  While I tried to
pass off the things I got as equally wonderful, my lack of social skills meant that
I was unsuccessful, while my classmates would seemingly and convincingly go on and on
about the fantastic things that they got.  They all seemed to be bragging about how
wonderful their lives and families were, and it hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As that stuff was happening at school, there were also issues
I had with how my extended family dealt with Christmas.  I mean, at 11 years old, how
could I explain to them that the music of Tchaikovsky appealed to me because of his use
of harmony and melody?  I just knew that I liked it and could get lost in that music
for hours.  So, when my mother asked what I wanted for Christmas from my extended
family, I asked for a Tchaikovsky cassette tape.  It was simple, it would not cost too
much, and it was something that I would appreciate.  Sounds logical, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up asking for that single cassette tape of Tchaikovsky for three years
straight.
I would never dream of asking my mother for it, because she was having a hard enough
time making sure we were cared for.  But as a request for Christmas from my
extended family, I was sure it was an easy request to fulfil.  Not so.
The first year, one of my older cousins gave me a Bart Simpson poster and a dancing
beer can, because &amp;ldquo;they were sure that is what I meant to ask for&amp;rdquo;.  The second year I
did indeed get a cassette tape, but one with the works of Beethoven.  When I asked
about the cassette tape, I was asked &amp;ldquo;aren&amp;rsquo;t they the same?&amp;rdquo;.  The third year, a year
in which I remember one of my younger cousins being responsible for me in the gift
exchange, I finally received a cassette tape of some of Tchaikovsky&amp;rsquo;s symphonies.  I
did not find out who that cousin was, but I wish I did so I could have thanked them&amp;hellip; I
played that tape until it wore out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those experiences left a bitter mark on my mind regarding Christmas.
Finding out more information about the gifts, I was able to figure out that the dancing
beer can was supposed to be a gag gift or a good joke.  The Beethoven tape? It was
bought two months before my mother gave them my Christmas list.  While it may not be
the right information to gleam from those events, my Autistic mind analyzed the facts
that I had gathered and came to a couple of conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first conclusion was that my extended family did not care about each other.  It was
about a good joke with the whole family there, or something that was bought at a sale
that they could pass off as good enough.  It was not about love or understanding, it
was about fulfilling a contract to present a gift.  The second conclusion was that even
though we were all good Catholics and went to mass in and around the holidays, most of
that was all for show.  One of the tenets that I learned growing up was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do unto others as you would have them do unto you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel of Luke, 6:31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my aunts and uncles asked each other for something for Christmas, I believe they
almost always received what they asked for.  How would they have felt if it took one
of their siblings three years to get it right?  I do not think they would have been
happy.  Furthermore, how would they have felt if they asked for something they really
did need, and instead got a joke gift and had everyone laughing at them.  How would
they feel then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my recollection, none of my extended family asked me or my mother what was so
important about Tchaikovsky that I would ask for it over a toy.  I just know that it
was not until I was in my 30s that one of my younger cousins asked.  The reason? In a
life where my Autistic mind was going the speed of thought, listening to those melodies
and harmonies helped me find peace and calmness for a brief amount of time.  I could
lose myself in them and forget about how difficult that the world was for me to
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I grew older, I was able to start figuring out how these things impacted my life
and how it colored my view of Christmas.  My loving wife has asked me for the last
ten years why I do not share her love of Christmas, and it is only recently that I have
been able to sort out parts of it.  It has been difficult to try and pull on all these
threads to try and figure it out but undertaking that task has helped me find some
peace with the subject. From those old threads of my Christmas experiences, I was able
to gather some things that I would like to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the years have passed, I have heard little bits of information here and there from
my trips back home that lead me to believe that a lot of my classmates were not always
as lucky as I was.  It was with a lot of sadness that I found out what a lot of
those classmates had to go through their own versions of hell in their own lives.  For
quite a few of them, those Christmas presents that they received were the only symbols
of love that they received from their parents.
For others, they felt a constant need to prove that they were better than others because
their families never made them feel like they were good enough.  I could go on with
other things I have heard about classmates over the years, but the picture is pretty
much the same.  Every one of those people had different forces impacting them in their
lives, and often, enough of them were negative and colored their perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the analytical part of my Autistic brain, I came to understand that
their bragging about Christmas gifts were mostly cries for help, not joyous refrains.
While I was upset with them growing up, regardless of their station in life I now hope
that each and every one of them finds peace in their own way. I came to the realization
that I was, and continue to be, lucky that I have always had a kind and caring mother
in my life. She has always been there for me and never left me feeling that having
only one parent in your life was not enough.  While it should be more common, it is not,
and that is sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that extent, I believe that Christmas should not be based on a calendar, but on a
state of mind.  We should
be helping people and making sure our children and each other are comfortable, loved,
and respected.  It should not be about making a special effort during Christmas to make
time for each other and be patient with each other, it should be a normal occurrence
in our daily lives.  I am not sure if this makes me seem naïve or if it just the way
that my Autistic mind works, but it is how I feel.  I do not care if it is kind
of mushy or idealistic.  Can anyone really argue with me that showing each other a
little more patience and respect would not be a positive thing in our chaotic world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another observation is that people are quick to point to the physical gifts that they
received at Christmas, but do not always pay attention to the other gifts throughout
the year.  Even though we did not have enough growing up, I have the utmost confidence
that I would not have made it to where I am today without my mother&amp;rsquo;s unconditional
love.  While she knew I was different from a young age, I never felt like I was a
&amp;ldquo;weird kid&amp;rdquo; to her, just her oldest son, who needed love just as much as her other
two kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, different people experience things differently, and we must make
our own efforts to understand people on their turf, not ours.  As someone with Autism,
I should not be expected to offer to explain myself and my Autism to people.  But if
someone were to ask me a question about how I perceive things and how they can help, I
would definitely be open to that.  I would like to think that if my relatives had asked
me that question about Tchaikovsky and I answered honestly that they would either
respect myself or my mother and help me find that 45 minutes of peace located on a
well-worn cassette tape.  I know I would gladly offer that gift to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after finding peace with the subject, I am not sure that a &amp;ldquo;love&amp;rdquo; of Christmas
is in the cards for me.  I do know that in my own life, either inspired by my mother&amp;rsquo;s
love or her teaching of &amp;ldquo;the Christmas spirit&amp;rdquo; to me, Christmas is just another day
to me as I simply try and apply those &amp;ldquo;Christmastime&amp;rdquo; principles to my life daily.  To
be honest, I have no clue on whether it is my Autism or my upbringing that
has got me to this place in my life, I just know that it is the path that I chose.  And
I feel good about that choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess you could say that it is my gift to those around me.  My gift to myself?
Letting go of some of those negative Christmas experiences each year.  Allowing myself
to forgive those people and hope that they find peace with their own person daemons.
I am not a religious person by nature, but I do know that the many holy books, the
Bible included, have some great verses.  Here is one I try and live by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new commandment I give to you, that you love one another: just as I have loved you, you also are to love one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel of John, 13:34&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry></feed>