<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jack's Digital Workbench - Autism</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/feeds/autism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jackdewinter.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Autism And How It Affects My View of Christmas</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2020/12/15/autism-and-how-it-affects-my-view-of-christmas/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2020-12-15:/2020/12/15/autism-and-how-it-affects-my-view-of-christmas/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people in my life have been very understanding, but as always, there are a decent
number of people that have left some lasting negative impacts.  Some of those people I
blame for their actions, and some of those people were just reacting to me and how
my Autism appeared …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people in my life have been very understanding, but as always, there are a decent
number of people that have left some lasting negative impacts.  Some of those people I
blame for their actions, and some of those people were just reacting to me and how
my Autism appeared to them.  But equally important to how I appeared to them was my
Autism and how it has affected my view of Christmas throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say that I was diagnosed with Autism in my 40s, that does not mean that I did not
have Autism before that.  It just means instead of &amp;ldquo;the weird guy with Autism&amp;rdquo;, I was
just the &amp;ldquo;the weird guy&amp;rdquo;.  And back when I was a kid, I definitely was &amp;ldquo;the weird kid&amp;rdquo;.
Contrary to the modern definition of Autism, the definition of Autism when I was a kid
was someone with below-average intellect who had severe problems interacting with the
world.  I did not have the benefit of any helpful labels and programs to help me
succeed, such as the help that my son was able to get throughout his childhood.  It was
just me trying to figure things out as I went, often feeling alone and alien, wanting
to fit in with my peers, but not knowing how to even start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is where my negative view of Christmas started, based on a strong dislike of what
I perceived to be the over-commercialization of Christmas.  As I have been trying to
understand myself better over the years, it has been hard for me to disentangle two
aspects of this dislike from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
original reason that I disliked Christmas was indeed a selfish one: our family did not
have enough growing up.  My mom is one of the most important people in my life, and
each year I saw her struggle throughout the year to make sure we had our basic
necessities and whatever other reasonable things she could get for us.  It pissed me
off that my father was almost never in the picture.  The thought of my mother having
to ask our local church or food bank for help and for presents, either made me feel
embarrassed and mad at the same time.  With the kind heart that I know my mother has,
I am pretty confident
that she felt like she should have been a better mother, even though that was not in
the cards. For me, even though my mom did everything for us out love for us,
Christmas was a time when I always felt more negative emotions that positive ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is where the second aspect kicks in: my peers.  I remember the feeling of
dread that preceded going back to school after Christmas break.  Each year, I would go
back to school and everyone in the class
would be bragging about the wonderful things they got for Christmas.  While I tried to
pass off the things I got as equally wonderful, my lack of social skills meant that
I was unsuccessful, while my classmates would seemingly and convincingly go on and on
about the fantastic things that they got.  They all seemed to be bragging about how
wonderful their lives and families were, and it hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As that stuff was happening at school, there were also issues
I had with how my extended family dealt with Christmas.  I mean, at 11 years old, how
could I explain to them that the music of Tchaikovsky appealed to me because of his use
of harmony and melody?  I just knew that I liked it and could get lost in that music
for hours.  So, when my mother asked what I wanted for Christmas from my extended
family, I asked for a Tchaikovsky cassette tape.  It was simple, it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t cost too
much, and it was something that I would appreciate.  Sounds logical, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up asking for that single cassette tape of Tchaikovsky for three years
straight.
I would never dream of asking my mother for it, because she was having a hard enough
time making sure we were cared for.  But as a request for Christmas from my
extended family, I was sure it was an easy request to fulfil.  Not so.
The first year, one of my older cousins gave me a Bart Simpson poster and a dancing
beer can, because &amp;ldquo;they were sure that is what I meant to ask for&amp;rdquo;.  The second year I
did indeed get a cassette tape, but one with the works of Beethoven.  When I asked
about the cassette tape, I was asked &amp;ldquo;aren&amp;rsquo;t they the same?&amp;rdquo;.  The third year, a year
in which I remember one of my younger cousins being responsible for me in the gift
exchange, I finally received a cassette tape of some of Tchaikovsky&amp;rsquo;s symphonies.  I
don&amp;rsquo;t know who that cousin was, but I wish I did so I could have thanked them&amp;hellip; I
played that tape until it wore out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those experiences left a bitter mark on my mind regarding Christmas.
Finding out more information about the gifts, I was able to figure out that the dancing
beer can was supposed to be a gag gift or a good joke.  The Beethoven tape? It was
bought two months before my mother gave them my Christmas list.  While it may not be
the right information to gleam from those events, my Autistic mind analyzed the facts
that I had gathered and came to a couple of conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first conclusion was that my extended family did not care about each other.  It was
about a good joke with the whole family there, or something that was bought at a sale
that they could pass off as good enough.  It was not about love or understanding, it
was about fulfilling a contract to present a gift.  The second conclusion was that even
though we were all good Catholics and went to mass in and around the holidays, most of
that was all for show.  One of the tenets that I learned growing up was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do unto others as you would have them do unto you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel of Luke, 6:31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my aunts and uncles asked each other for something for Christmas, I believe they
almost always received what they asked for.  How would they have felt if it took one
of their siblings three years to get it right?  I don&amp;rsquo;t think they would have been
happy.  Furthermore, how would they have felt if they asked for something they really
did need, and instead got a joke gift and had everyone laughing at them.  How would
they feel then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my recollection, none of my extended family asked me or my mother what was so
important about Tchaikovsky that I would ask for it over a toy.  I just know that it
wasn&amp;rsquo;t until I was in my 30s that one of my younger cousins asked.  The reason? In a
life where my Autistic mind was going the speed of thought, listening to those melodies
and harmonies helped me find peace and calmness for a brief amount of time.  I could
lose myself in them, and forget about how difficult that the world was for me to
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I grew older, I was able to start figuring out how these things impacted my life
and how it colored my view of Christmas.  My loving wife has asked me for the last
ten years why I don&amp;rsquo;t share her love of Christmas, and it is only recently that I have
been able to sort out parts of it.  It has been difficult to try and pull on all these
threads to try and figure it out, but undertaking that task has helped me find some
peace with the subject. From those old threads of my Christmas experiences, I was able
to gather some things that I would like to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the years have passed, I have heard little bits of information here and there from
my trips back home that lead me to believe that a lot of my classmates weren&amp;rsquo;t always
as lucky as I was.  It was with a lot of sadness that I found out what a lot of
those classmates had to go through their own versions of hell in their own lives.  For
quite a few of them, those Christmas presents that they received were the only symbols
of love that they received from their parents.
For others, they felt a constant need to prove that they were better than others because
their families never made them feel like they were good enough.  I could go on with
other things I have heard about classmates over the years, but the picture is pretty
much the same.  Every one of those people had different forces impacting them in their
lives, and more often than not, enough of them were negative and colored their
perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the analytical part of my Autistic brain, I came to understand that
their bragging about Christmas gifts were mostly cries for help, not joyous refrains.
While I was upset with them growing up, regardless of their station in life I now hope
that each and every one of them finds peace in their own way. I came to the realization
that I was, and continue to be, lucky that I have always had a kind and caring mother
in my life. She has always been there for me and never left me feeling that having
only one parent in your life wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough.  While it should be more common, it is not,
and that is sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that extent, I believe that Christmas should not be based on a calendar, but on a
state of mind.  We should
be helping people and making sure our children and each other are comfortable, loved,
and respected.  It shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be about making a special effort during Christmas to make
time for each other and be patient with each other, it should be a normal occurrence
in our daily lives.  I am not sure if this makes me seem naïve or if it just the way
that my my Autistic mind works, but it is how I feel.  I don&amp;rsquo;t care if it is kind
of mushy or idealistic.  Can anyone really argue with me that showing each other a
little more patience and respect would not be a positive thing in our chaotic world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another observation is that people are quick to point to the physical gifts that they
received at Christmas, but don&amp;rsquo;t always pay attention to the other gifts throughout
the year.  Even though we didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough growing up, I have the utmost confidence
that I would not have made it to where I am today without my mother&amp;rsquo;s unconditional
love.  While she knew I was different from a young age, I never felt like I was a
&amp;ldquo;weird kid&amp;rdquo; to her, just her oldest son, who needed love just as much as her other
two kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, different people experience things differently, and we have to make
our own efforts to understand people on their turf, not ours.  As someone with Autism,
I should not be expected to offer to explain myself and my Autism to people.  But if
someone was to ask me a question about how I perceive things and how they can help, I
would definitely be open to that.  I would like to think that if my relatives had asked
me that question about Tchaikovsky and I answered honestly, that they would either
respect myself or my mother and help me find that 45 minutes of peace located on a
well-worn cassette tape.  I know I would gladly offer that gift to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after finding peace with the subject, I am not sure that a &amp;ldquo;love&amp;rdquo; of Christmas
is in the cards for me.  I do know that in my own life, either inspired by my mother&amp;rsquo;s
love or her teaching of &amp;ldquo;the Christmas spirit&amp;rdquo; to me, Christmas is just another day
to me as I simply try and apply those &amp;ldquo;Christmastime&amp;rdquo; principles to my life on a daily
basis.  To be honest, I have no clue on whether it is my Autism or my upbringing that
has got me to this place in my life, I just know that it is the path that I chose.  And
I feel good about that choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess you could say that it is my gift to those around me.  My gift to myself?
Letting go of some of those negative Christmas experiences each year.  Allowing myself
to forgive those people and hope that they find peace with their own person daemons.
I am not a religious person by nature, but I do know that the many holy books, the
Bible included, have some great verses.  Here is one I try and live by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new commandment I give to you, that you love one another: just as I have loved you, you also are to love one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel of John, 13:34&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry><entry><title>Autism, Stress, and Anxiety</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2020/11/11/autism-stress-and-anxiety/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2020-11-11:/2020/11/11/autism-stress-and-anxiety/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know.  I really don&amp;rsquo;t know.&amp;rdquo;  Those were the last words I said before a
solid minute&amp;rsquo;s worth of silence.  After being married for seven years, my wife and I
had a &amp;ldquo;heated discussion&amp;rdquo; that was almost an argument.   That was unusual in itself.
But even …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know.  I really don&amp;rsquo;t know.&amp;rdquo;  Those were the last words I said before a
solid minute&amp;rsquo;s worth of silence.  After being married for seven years, my wife and I
had a &amp;ldquo;heated discussion&amp;rdquo; that was almost an argument.   That was unusual in itself.
But even more unusual was that I was at a loss of words.  Her question?  &amp;ldquo;How can I
help?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, our marriage is an interesting one already.  I am a software guy with a diagnosed
case of Autism, with an anxiety disorder and sensory overload disorder to boot.  My
diagnosis is such that unless I tell people I have Autism or they know what to look
for, I can often hide under the radar. But even so, it does have significant impacts on
my day-to-day life.  In contrast, my wife is a lawyer that has a heart of gold,
preferring that people play together nicely.  When they don&amp;rsquo;t, she is the one that is
not afraid to step in and do or say what needs to resolve the situation.  But uniting
us together is the fact that we both have big hearts and open minds.  The combination
of that with humor and laughter has always been a major component to our success in
marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case, I was stumped.  Earlier in the day she had told me that she wanted
to go on a vacation to Florida with her family.  During a pandemic.  On an airplane.
With people she doesn&amp;rsquo;t know around her.  I really didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to say.  I remember
ranting and raving about it, but as to what I said at that moment, I don&amp;rsquo;t
remember too much of that.  It was all a blur.  My logic and my emotions were all over
the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is where things get interesting:  I know we have two different points of view
on things like this.  While my wife is weird (heck, she married me!), she is solidly
neurotypical with only a middling amount of introvert.  Even with her being cooped up
in our house since April, she has been going into her workplace once or twice a week
since our state allowed it during the summer.  Even with this, I can tell that not
being able to get out and stretch her legs among people is chewing away at her
sanity.  I know that her going on vacation with her family is a good thing for her. It
is what she needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it is a completely different equation.  Starting with the little things,
going on a vacation with crowds of other people around is just not a lot of fun for
someone with sensory overload disorder.  Trying to mitigate the effects of that disorder
is many times more exhausting than dealing with anything else. Adding to that, my
anxiety disorder and my Autism are acting the part of tag team wrestlers. My Autism
takes the first shot with an elbow, keeping me isolated from groups of people
that I know care about me.  Then my anxiety disorder takes control with an
&lt;a href="https://prowrestling.fandom.com/wiki/Wrestling_throws#Irish_whip"&gt;Irish Whip&lt;/a&gt;,
either complaining that I am getting too little information about the current state
of the pandemic and economy, or too much information.  Then my Autism tags in with a
high-five, hyper-focusing on one little thing that I think I heard or didn&amp;rsquo;t hear.
Finally, my anxiety tags in with a
&lt;a href="https://prowrestling.fandom.com/wiki/Wrestling_throws#Hurricanrana"&gt;hurricanrana&lt;/a&gt;,
trying to figure out all the possible situations that can happen and ways to deal
with each of them. &lt;sup id="fnref:wrestling"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:wrestling"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I struggled to figure out what metaphor to use to explain the vicious cycle that
escalates in my head.  While I haven&amp;rsquo;t watched professional wrestling in years, I
believe it is the best metaphor by far.  At its heart, professional wrestling is a
show.  For me to communicate with people every day, I must act a bit to communicate
clearly. Professional wrestling contains the good guys, or
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Face_(professional_wrestling)"&gt;faces&lt;/a&gt;, and the
bad guys, or
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heel_(professional_wrestling)"&gt;heels&lt;/a&gt;.  Just like
in the shows, sometimes my positivity and clarity win, and sometimes my anxiety and
lack of connection with others wins.  And as anyone who has followed wrestling will
tell you, behind the bright white smiles, coifed hair, and shiny outfits are people
that are often hurting doing the thing they love to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about how to answer that question as I write this article, where am I now? I
still don&amp;rsquo;t know.  I do know that in terms of where I am, I am currently fighting
my own personal wrestling match day-by-day.  There are some days where the good guys
win and some days where the bad guys win.  Some of the days I am acting for my
audience, and some of the days I am trying to be my honest self with them.  Just like a
wrestler needs to understand where they are in the ring relative to the others, I need
to understand where my wife is relative to where she needs to be.  And yes, somedays
I am controlling my anxiety and Autism, and somedays it controls me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And forgive me if I it seems like I am singling myself out from the people around me
and the stress they are experiencing.  But there are two things that I feel make a
big difference.  My Autism and anxiety do amplify each other, sometimes out of control.
Also, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the option of resorting to things like alcohol or other things to
help me forget for a while.  Quite the opposite, those things tend to amplify
how I feel even more.  I don&amp;rsquo;t get a break&amp;hellip; but I am okay with that.  This is
something I have dealt with every day of my life, this tug-of-war going on inside of
my head.  Yeah, it is exhausting.  It is so unbearably exhausting at times.  But the
flip side of that is: I know I can handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I still don&amp;rsquo;t have a good answer for her question, I am working on it.  What I do
know is that our solutions to how to deal with the stress of this pandemic are
going to be on opposite sides of the spectrum.  As much as it would be a terrible idea
for me to think about, I believe that her flying down to Florida with her family is one
of the better things she can do for herself.  In contrast to her approach, I do know
that a lot of the things that I need to do are small and personal.  More mental
breaks.  Increased exercise.  Making better choices when eating.  No big silver
bullets, just little things that add up over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I guess that is okay.  The important thing I realized in all this is that we are
asking ourselves the right questions.  &amp;ldquo;How are you?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;What are you feeling?&amp;rdquo;, and the
important one: &amp;ldquo;How can I help?&amp;rdquo;  I know I don&amp;rsquo;t have that answer for her on that last
one, I am working on it.  I do know that part of my answer is this article.  It&amp;rsquo;s
making sure others, people with Autism or not, ask themselves, their friends, and their
loved ones those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:wrestling"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Southern Ontario in the 80s.  Yes, I watched wrestling.  Everyone I knew did.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:wrestling" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Autism"></category><category term="Autism"></category></entry></feed>