<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jack's Digital Workbench - Personal</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jackdewinter.github.io/</id><updated>2022-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Debugging... The Story Continues</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/19/debugging-the-story-continues/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-09-19:/2022/09/19/debugging-the-story-continues/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/12/my-love-of-short-film/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, about my love of film,
especially short film and how it inspires me.  In this article, I am going to
talk again on the artform called debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="if-it-was-easy-everyone-would-do-it"&gt;If It Was Easy, Everyone Would Do It&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#if-it-was-easy-everyone-would-do-it" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That title just about sums it up for me.  Debugging …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/12/my-love-of-short-film/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, about my love of film,
especially short film and how it inspires me.  In this article, I am going to
talk again on the artform called debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="if-it-was-easy-everyone-would-do-it"&gt;If It Was Easy, Everyone Would Do It&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#if-it-was-easy-everyone-would-do-it" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That title just about sums it up for me.  Debugging is not always an easy task
to undertake.  It takes brute force, luck, and stubbornness. I need to make sure
that I clear my mind of distractions, but also know when I need distractions to
reset my mind so I can start again. At times it can feel like you are mentally
balancing on a rope, without knowing how thick the rope is or how far off the
ground it is.  And you have to be okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any readers that think I may be exagerating with that opening paragraph, I
am going to try and prove that I am not exagerating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="start-with-something-simple"&gt;Start With Something Simple&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#start-with-something-simple" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start proving my point, I am going to start with something that is relatively
easy to figure out.  When running this code, it looks like it should succeed,
but it does not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;2.2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;3.3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, when I run this through the Python terminal, I get the
following output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
AssertionError
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any developer with experience, one look at this code will quickly lead them
to question how Python handles floating point numbers.  In this case, the value
of &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; is assigned the value of &lt;code&gt;3.3000000000000003&lt;/code&gt; and does not match the
value in the &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; statement’s conditional. From the Python documentation
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3.10/tutorial/floatingpoint.html?highlight=floating%20point"&gt;on floating point values&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most decimal fractions cannot be represented exactly as binary
fractions. A consequence is that, in general, the decimal floating-point numbers
you enter are only approximated by the binary floating-point numbers actually
stored in the machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="adding-in-some-complexity"&gt;Adding In Some Complexity&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#adding-in-some-complexity" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduating from that example, the next example is a bit more nuanced:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running this through the Python terminal, we get the same output as above, with
an assert occuring on the last line.  Even as someone who has used Python for over
five years, this one initially stumped me.  But due to my debugging skills, I added
one line to that example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one line provided output that was pivotal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;class 'float'&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one piece of information lead me to
&lt;a href="https://realpython.world/basics/division-in-python.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on
Real Python that talks about division and integer division. The article
talks about various aspects of division and remainders in Python, and was
an interesting read.  It also gave me something to think about as I
am debugging other scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="taking-steps-to-tame-the-chaos"&gt;Taking Steps To Tame The Chaos&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#taking-steps-to-tame-the-chaos" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first example outlined a situation that occurs in most programming languages.
Most languages do not have built-in support for exacting floating point values.
Instead, the default is to approximate floating point values using binary values.
The key there is the word “approximate” as various calculations end up being
off by an extremely small amount.  But that amount is just enough to make conditionals
fail when they look like they should succeed, when the fail. To rememdy this problem,
the develop needs to know about the &lt;code&gt;//&lt;/code&gt; integer division operator which provides
the behavior that most developers expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second example is something that strikes polyglot developers more than
single language developers, but can be a blindspot that hits a junior developer.
Different languages have specific ways of handling specific situations.  In Python,
dividing one integer by another integer results in a float.  However, in most modern
languages, the result would be an integer.  It depends on the viewpoint as to whether
that is a good thing or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are concepts that are handled coherently across languages.  Sticking to
examples related to floating point math, fixed point math is supported in Python using
the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/decimal.html"&gt;decimal&lt;/a&gt; module. Supported with
a similar name in other modern languages, one part of the Python module definition
stands out clearly in the documentation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decimal “is based on a floating-point model which was designed with people in mind,
and necessarily has a paramount guiding principle – computers must provide an
arithmetic that works in the same way as the arithmetic that people learn at school.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is not built-in support to properly handle these two examples, modules like
the &lt;code&gt;decimal&lt;/code&gt; module provide easy-to-use alternatives that address these issues.  But
it takes learning and experience to know what the alternatives are and when to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="using-language-support"&gt;Using Language Support&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#using-language-support" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that Python has going for it is that it does not statically type every
variable that is created.  Instead, a value is assigned to a type that “makes the
most sense”.  Given a value of &lt;code&gt;"xxx"&lt;/code&gt;, a string makes the most sense.  Given a
value of &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;, an integer makes the most sense.  Given a value of &lt;code&gt;(1, False)&lt;/code&gt;,
a tuple makes the most sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while that is often a boon in Python development, it can make things a bit
crazy when debugging.  When debugging in Python, I have either had to use debug
output or traverse multiple functions to determine the type and value of a
variable.  While I do spend some time in Python’s real-time debugger, the volume
of tests in my projects often prevent me from spending any significant time in
the debugger.  Instead, I needed an alternative that would at least help me
figure out those values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up with proposals to determine the value of variables was an easy problem
to solve.  Python has a very robust built-in logger that is easy to setup and use.
But that part of the solution requires me to complete parts of the code before I
can run the code to produce the log entries.  And that did not help me much with
my type issues.  Then I started paying attention to &lt;a href="http://mypy-lang.org/"&gt;MyPy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MyPy is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;an optional static type checker for Python that aims to combine the benefits of
dynamic (or “duck”) typing and static typing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MyPy type checking is run on Python code as part of a “compile phase”. While
it is optional, once a module has started to implement static typing in one or
more functions, warnings will be emitted if typed Python code calls into an
untyped function.  But the good part of that process is that most of the type
annotations in MyPy are simple and easy to use. Rewriting the above example
using type annotations leads to a function looking somewhat similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;my_func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, I have been more verbose than I usually am, but that is only
to highlight a point.  By ensuring that every variable reference in the function
is an integer, the attempt to assign &lt;code&gt;x / 2&lt;/code&gt; will still work in Python, but will
raise a type error in MyPy.  Just having that capability alone saves time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="multiplying-that-by-orders-of-multitude"&gt;Multiplying That By Orders Of Multitude&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#multiplying-that-by-orders-of-multitude" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons that I have strived to keep the various parts of the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project separate from
each other is because understanding and debugging complex systems suck. When
I say that they suck, what I am really saying is that as humans, we all have our
limits in keeping multiple values and multiple trains of thought going in our
heads at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a simple system, such as the &lt;code&gt;my_func&lt;/code&gt; function in the above example,
keeping each concept in my head to figure out the problem is a relatively easy
problem to solve.  With my experience to supercharge my debugging skills, determining
the issue in a small system like that is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as complexity grows in the source code, the complexity of debugging that
source code grows at an even faster rate.  When writing code, I typically work
towards a single goal before moving on to the next goal.  If I try to keep too
much in my head with respect to the code, I often fail at that task.  By keeping
things simple, I retain a clear picture in my head which allows me to develop
the source code with the same clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way in which I debug code approaches the problem of debugging compex systems
with a similar approach.  To ensure that I keep that clarity, I make it a habit
in my projects to using logging effectively.  This means outputing the current
state of a variable at a crucial point and also logging crucial paths taking due
to conditional statements.  By performing these actions, I provide a trail
of breadcrumbs that I can refer back to in order to clarify the picture that I
am debugging from.  I can then focus on the local picture, and determine if the
picture that the logs are telling is the same as the picture that I have in my
head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debugging effectively for me is all about keeping a clear picture in my head and
making sure that I can shift that picture as needed.  But that is not always
enough to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="debugging-is-a-lot-of-hard-work"&gt;Debugging Is A Lot of Hard Work&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#debugging-is-a-lot-of-hard-work" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this relate to the whitespace work of the last couple of weeks?  The
honest answer is that I paid a lot of attention to the above concepts that I have
developed over many years, and it was still failing me.  Sometimes systems are
complex enough that it is hard to decompose them into small enough pictures that
make for effective debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is what happened with the last remaining issue dealing with whitespaces.
With all the other issues resolve, I had a single issue remaining where the
following Markdown generated an &lt;code&gt;AssertionError&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;quote&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;another&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;quote&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In trying to keep things simple, I was able to quickly determine what the issue
was.  When the parser recursed to handle the text past the first block quote on
the second line, it was not recognizing the remaining text as another block quote
with its own text.  Furthermore, because that parsing was off, an assert was
failing because the indent calculations for the produced tokens were off as well.
Basically, it was not working properly, and I had at least two possible reasons
for the failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the two weeks that I was working on the other whitespace issues, I went back
to this issue multiple times.  Even with the various parts of the system somewhat
isolated from each other, the parsing of tokens is a somewhat complex system.
Part of that complexity is just because parsing in itself tends to be complex, with
most parsers supporting forward scanning as a primary mode and backward scanning
where needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PyMarkdown project is no different, with multiple possible areas to check on
what could be causing that behavior.  I have found through experience that sometimes
the most effective debugging behavior is not given up.  Just sticking to my confidence
that I can debug the code and determine what the issue is.  And sometimes, that means
trying twenty different paths just to find the one path that works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was on that twentieth try that I found my answer.  In that one specific
example above, the &lt;code&gt;leading_space&lt;/code&gt; variable for that Block Quote token is assigned
the leading spaces for both the first and second lines.  When that token’s
&lt;code&gt;leading_space&lt;/code&gt; variable was then used in a subsequent calculation, the result
was the calculation of the length of all the leading space for that Block Quote
token, not just the last line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moral"&gt;The Moral&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#the-moral" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having talent is essential in developing system to meet the needs they were designed
for.  Even without a lot of talent, a person can still be taught different
concepts and ideas that build their development experience. But when it comes to
debugging, I put more faith in having a clear picture in my head and knowing that
I am stubborn enough to not give up easily, than to bank on experinece and talent.
[more]&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="markdown linter"></category><category term="core linter"></category></entry><entry><title>My Love of Short Film</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/12/my-love-of-short-film/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-09-12:/2022/09/12/my-love-of-short-film/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/06/inspiration-comes-at-weird-moments-in-our-life/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about
how inspiration struck me for that article… and when.  Continuing along with that
train of thought, I thought I would talk about my love of film, especially short film.
Especially how it inspires me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="it-started-a-long-time-ago"&gt;It Started A Long Time Ago&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#it-started-a-long-time-ago" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/09/06/inspiration-comes-at-weird-moments-in-our-life/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about
how inspiration struck me for that article… and when.  Continuing along with that
train of thought, I thought I would talk about my love of film, especially short film.
Especially how it inspires me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="it-started-a-long-time-ago"&gt;It Started A Long Time Ago&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#it-started-a-long-time-ago" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think back to the most memorable times of my life, there are usually
movies associated with each of those moments.  Before my parents split up, I can remember
watching Godzilla movies like &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/godzilla-vs-mechagodzilla/"&gt;Godzilla Vs Mechagodzilla&lt;/a&gt;
with my cousins at their house.  I can remember the many
Christmastimes where my mother and I watched &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/white-christmas/"&gt;White Christmas&lt;/a&gt;
and sang along with the songs that we knew by heart.  I can remember my mother
saving up money so that we could see &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/star-wars/"&gt;Star Wars&lt;/a&gt;
together as a family (minus my dad) after my parents divorced.  And after my youngest son was born, I
fondly remember going to see &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-country-bears/"&gt;The Country Bears&lt;/a&gt;
with my daughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can go on and on, with interesting memories of movies and the times and
circumstances around those movies.  But there are also movies that I watched just
to watch a movie and see if the people behind the movie were going to do something
interesting.  As someone who is creative in his personal life and professional
life, it interests me to see what people come up with.
Be it an interesting plot twist or a very predictable plot twist done
with style, it does not really matter.  It is the craft with which these
movies are made that speaks to me.  And different movies speak to me in different
ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let me start with &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/avatar/"&gt;Avatar&lt;/a&gt;.  I
have had interesting discussions on whether this is a good movie with many people.
Some people say it is overrated and some say the acting is wooden. Some people say
there is too much animation and some people say there is enough animation.  I think
they are all missing the point. From my viewpoint, James Cameron had a vision of
how he wanted the movie to look and sound, and he delivered on that vision.
I personally liked the movie’s other qualities, as did many other people apparently
judging by the box office numbers. But for me it was more about the cinematography,
the animation, the audio, and the creativity that made this a fantastic movie for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the coin, there is &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/flash-gordon-1980/"&gt;Flash Gordon&lt;/a&gt;.
I do admit, this is one of the corniest favorite movies of mine, but I will not
back down from saying it is a great movie.  First off, I am a major fan of the rock
group Queen, and they wrote and performed most of the music in the movie.
Next are the visuals.  The original &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/flash-gordon/"&gt;Flash Gordon&lt;/a&gt;
movies came out in the late 1930s and I passionately believe that the producers of the
1980 film tried to keep the look and feel of the 1930s movie, while upgrading them
to be a bit psychedelic for the 1980s.  Finally… it is a movie that does not take
itself seriously.  From my point of view, which is what completes the movie.  Though
I must admit, seeing &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/actor/brian-blessed/"&gt;Brian Blessed&lt;/a&gt; as
a hawkman still makes me smile to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am looking for a new movie to watch, I am looking for a wise way to invest a
good ninety minutes or more in something that may interest me.  It can be
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-rocky-horror-picture-show/"&gt;schlocky&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/bellargregory/list/lord-of-the-rings/"&gt;classic&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/moon/"&gt;thought provoking&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/solaris/"&gt;mind-bending&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/voyage-to-the-bottom-of-the-sea/"&gt;old-time science fiction&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/forbidden-planet/"&gt;golden-age science fiction&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/carrie-1976/"&gt;horror&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-devil-and-daniel-mouse/"&gt;downright silly&lt;/a&gt;.
It really does not matter to me.  It just needs to be something where I can
say “yeah, I don’t mind investing that time.”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="short-films"&gt;Short Films&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#short-films" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As life goes on, the things that you need to do in life build up and consume time.  In
addition, that thing called “energy”, which seems to be in shorter supply these days than
it was in my youth.  On top of that, instead of most movies being ninety minutes as
they were when I was growing up, it is common for movies to be around the two hour
mark, with movies with good stories edging closer to three hours.  But the longer
a movie is, the more it needs to deliver on its value to the movie watcher.  If it
does not deliver, people get bored, give it bad reviews, and stop watching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me use the Rocky Horror Picture Show as an example of that.  It is one of the
campiest movies I have ever seen, and I love it!  But at a run time of one hundred
minutes, I must admit that I wish that the movie ended about seven to eight minutes
earlier than it did.  I feel that there are parts of the movie that could have been
tightened up or dropped on the cutting room floor.  But with a run time of
one hundred minutes (and me singing along with the songs in the movie), I would
argue that it has a good length for the film that it is.  A longer movie would
have to have something stellar added in to make
up for the added run time.  And I just do not think that would be possible with
that movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer to the run time issue for me are short films.
Short films offer me a chance to roll the dice with many small movies and see
if I like what they are delivering.  Most of these films are between twelve minutes
and thirty minutes in length, allowing me to watch multiple short films in a single
night.  Because I have interesting tastes in movies, I can usually follow the
YouTube recommendations and find interesting themes to go with.  And because the
run time is so low, I do not feel bad if I watch something that is a waste of
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest though, I rarely skip through a movie without giving it at least
three chances.  If I find myself looking at what is next in my queue during the movie, that is
one strike.  If I find myself looking to see what other people have said about
the movie during the movie, that is another strike.  If I find myself wishing the movie would
just end… NOW… that is the third strike.  If it fails on all three counts,
it is likely not to get any better with any added runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="everyone-starts-somewhere"&gt;Everyone Starts Somewhere&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#everyone-starts-somewhere" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky in life, you get to see the early work of someone who later
becomes famous.  I remember talking to someone from nearby Brantford, Ontario who
saw Wayne Gretzky play for his high school team before making it big.  The
man said that he could just see Gretzky naturally figure out how things worked
in that ice rink.  He recalled watching Gretzky play later in life for the Edmonton
Oilers and the Los Angeles Kings, telling me that parts of his play style matured
and parts just remained as iconic as the first time he saw him.  It was just
magic for that hockey fan getting to see someone at both ends of a stellar career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the film world, that person is George Lucas.  Lucas wrote and directed
the film &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/electronic-labyrinth-thx-1138-4eb/"&gt;Electronic Labyrinth: THX 1138 4EB&lt;/a&gt;
while he was still in film school.  After school Lucas expanded on that fifteen
minute short film and directed &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/thx-1138/"&gt;THX 1138&lt;/a&gt;
before directing the &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/star-wars/"&gt;Star Wars&lt;/a&gt; movies
and producing &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/producer/george-lucas-1/"&gt;other movies&lt;/a&gt;,
including the &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/raiders-of-the-lost-ark/"&gt;Indiana Jones&lt;/a&gt;
movies and television series.  But without that first movie and its fifteen
minute run length, it is entirely possible that the rest of his movie career
might not have taken off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And especially with smart phones being so advanced these days, it is easier
to express your creativity than ever before.  There are plenty of people
that have promising ideas and just want to get them out there. And to be fair,
there are lots of people with so-so ideas and nasty ideas as well.  But by
the time I find those movies, they have usually been filtered out of what
I am searching for.  But whether I am seeing the next Gretzky, the next Lucas,
or just someone living out their dream to direct a movie, if I can
see their creativity, it is okay with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short films are a godsend for me.  I get to relax and watch something to see
if it piques my interest, and I get to see if someone might be doing something
interesting enough that I want to see more of their films.  That is something
that I consider inspiring.  Any decent talent can make the second Star Wars
movie, but it took Lucas, his creativity, and the willingness to put himself
out there to make the first Star Wars movie.  That is what these people are
doing… being creative and taking a chance that what they produce will
resonate with viewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is what I consider inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="short film"></category></entry><entry><title>Dealing With The Ups and Downs</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/08/08/dealing-with-the-ups-and-downs/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-08-08:/2022/08/08/dealing-with-the-ups-and-downs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Upfront, I want to add this disclaimer for any relatives that may decide
to read this article.  I am going to be honest about how I felt and
what we talked about on my trip.  You may not agree with what I say or what we
decided, but our parents …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Upfront, I want to add this disclaimer for any relatives that may decide
to read this article.  I am going to be honest about how I felt and
what we talked about on my trip.  You may not agree with what I say or what we
decided, but our parents asked us to make sure they were taken care of, and their
wishes followed.  All three of us talked about what they had asked for, and
while we all agreed, I am the eldest son. If you want to blame anyone for things
not going your way, blame me.  My shoulders are wide enough and strong enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, the last two weeks have been one heck of a roller coaster ride
for me personally.  From joyful highs to mournful lows, I have seen it all
in the last two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joyous highs were all about my brother and his longtime girlfriend
getting married in Lunenburg, Nova Scotia on 30 July.  Not one to shy away
from doing things with a bit of pomp and circumstance, the wedding party
was a sight to see.  The women were all dressed in lovely dresses and beautiful
shows, and the men were dressed in khakis, Hawaiian shirts, and sandals.  The
thing is, knowing my brother and his now wife (and my new sister!), that was not
out of character.  It just worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we left the hotel, a wonderful gentleman named Colin (hope I got the name
right, it was a busy day!) bagpiped us from the hotel to the dock where we
boarded the sailing ship to take us out into the bay.  Even through all of
fuss of getting everyone on board, Colin played strongly and consistently
until it was time to cast off.  After waiting almost ten years for this
wedding, my brother&amp;rsquo;s wife did not want to do anything second rate.  A
wonderful sailing vessel with a wonderful crew, and a wedding on the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more interesting was that the rain that happened that day did not seem
to dampen anyone&amp;rsquo;s spirits in the least.  Sure, it meant donning rain ponchos
for some of us and umbrellas for others, but everything was still a go with
everyone having big smiles on their faces.  And with the backdrop of the
Lunenburg lighthouse in the background, the minister presided over the ceremony
like the champ that we all knew her to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as luck would have it, with the speaking of the words &amp;ldquo;You may now kiss
the bride&amp;rdquo;, the rain stopped.  Within fifteen minutes, the sun was out and
within another half an hour, most of us were at least partially dry.  But it
didn&amp;rsquo;t matter in the least.  It was not about the weather.  It was not about
the sailboat.  It was not about the bagpiper.  It was about my brother and
his wife getting married.  And nothing was going to damper the happiness of
that event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the next morning, reality started to kick back in.  My wife and I had
planned a nice drive along the coast from Lunenburg to Peggy&amp;rsquo;s Cove, one
of the famous places in Canada.  The sun was shining, and the coast
was beautiful, but my mind was already starting to turn inward.  I tried
to suppress that urge inward during the drive, but it was a daunting task.
Finally, after suppressing the urge all day, I started to turn inward as
we rested at our hotel in Halifax for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had been over four years since the three of us had gotten together, so there
was much catching up to do.  Well, I say there was much catching up
to do, but really it was just listening to the same stories and information
we had heard on the phone calls we try and have each month.  Those same stories
just seemed to have a different shine to them when told in person.  Everything
just was &amp;ldquo;that much&amp;rdquo; better.  Of course, being a true Canadian, it did not
hurt that we talked over dinner or over that day&amp;rsquo;s Tim Horton run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the one thing I knew we needed to talk about before the end of the trip
were my parents.  We all knew the pieces of those stories, but we
all felt that it was important to make sure that we were all in unison going
forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easy one was my father. My father passed away recently in Halifax, with
specific instructions on how he wanted to be buried and where he wanted to be
buried.  The problem there was that it was back in the Toronto area, and my
brother and his wife would not be going back for a while.  They just finished
their wedding, my brother is finishing school, and his wife is working.  It
will happen when it happens, and we all agreed to adhere to my dad&amp;rsquo;s wishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any readers that have read my articles, they will know that my dad and
I were not close.  One of the reasons is that I believe my dad was on the
Autism spectrum, just like me and my son.  Connection with other people was always
difficult for him, and I remember a handful of conversations where I believe
he was trying to understand why that happened, but to no avail.  I sincerely
believe he tried, but he just did not have the tools or support to make it
happen.  Most of the other serious conversations that we had were about the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being born in 1933, my dad was in his teens during World War II.  I had heard
stories from him about how things were, but only a couple of times.  He really
did not want to remember it at all.  He did join the Belgian Army once he was
of age, but he developed PTSD from that stint in the army.  By the time I was
old enough to talk with him about it and understand parts of what he said, he either shied
away from talking about the war and the army or talked about it like tar was
dripping from his mouth.  I did not see my father cry that many times in my
life, but in each conversation that included the war, he always cried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between all those circumstances, he just got to a place where he
could not manage being a full-time father, and my parents got divorced.  It
took me a long time to process what happened and what the factors involved were.
I believe that having PTSD and probably having undiagnosed Autism played big
factors.  I think he would have stood a chance at being a good father if he had
been born forty years later, but it just was not so.  Without the understanding of PTSD
and Autism that we even had in the 90s, he did not stand a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can say a few things about my dad for certain.  He hated any war and tried to
avoid conflict.  He felt sorry that he could not be a better father and tried
to overcome that deficiency in his own way.  He often wanted to communicate; he
just did not have the tools to communicate effectively. Because of his hate
of war and conflict, he just wanted to be buried alongside other family members,
just as a normal person, leaving any of the military experience that he felt
ruined his life behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that agreed on, we turned to talk about my mother.  With her having late-stage
dementia, my sister moved my mother to a long-term care facility a couple of
months ago.  It was heartbreaking to have my sister describe her recent visit
with my mom, but I believe she thought it was the right thing to do.  Even so,
I almost started crying myself as my sister fought back the tears and described
her visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dementia is a vile disease that takes parts of the person away bit by bit
until only a shell is left.  It started with her forgetting certain things around
her home, such as whether she locked the door or whether she already had her
meals.  After she moved into an assisted care facility, she stabilized for a
while before more things disappeared from her mind.  Before long, she was walking
into other people&amp;rsquo;s rooms, thinking that it was her room she was walking into.
By the time she was moved to a long-term care facility, even that was mostly
gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was weird talking about my mom in the past tense, but it felt like the right
thing to do.  There was a person that looked like my mom in the pictures that
I saw. But according to my sister, she is not sure that there is anyone she
recognizes in that body anymore.  The only communication that my mom seems to
do is with people that are not there anymore.  We are not sure if she is replaying
memories in her mind or talking to people that have passed before her.  We
do not even know if she is aware of where she is.  But to us, as terrible as
it sounds, she is not there anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting agreement between the three of us on what to do when it is my mother&amp;rsquo;s
time, which was the easy part.  She was a devout Roman Catholic and wanted to
be buried beside her second husband by her home parish priest.  With the state
of air flights, the way they are, the only questions were around what will we do if we
cannot get a flight to Toronto when she passes away.  And we agreed that I will
try my best, and we will cross that bridge if and when it is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grieving about what is happening is the hard part though.  How do you imagine
a world without the one person who gave up her marriage without a second though
because of the effects of my father&amp;rsquo;s PTSD?  Someone who was there to listen,
whether she agreed with you or not.  Someone who gave back to her community
in any way she could up until the dementia made it dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only good news is that the meeting with my siblings I think
helped the grieving and healing processes along.  But it is going to take
a long time for me to process this.  Step by step, day by day.  Remembering
the good moments of both parents, whether they were only a couple or whether
they were as bountiful as the flowers that were always in my mother&amp;rsquo;s
gardens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Confidence... One Bad Apple</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/07/18/confidence-one-bad-apple/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-07-18:/2022/07/18/confidence-one-bad-apple/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/07/12/are-scenario-tests-worth-it/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked
about my progress in adding scenario tests for the nested container scenarios
for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project.
In this article, I talk about the struggles to regain my confidence that I have been having
since my crash at the &lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/"&gt;end of May&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/07/12/are-scenario-tests-worth-it/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked
about my progress in adding scenario tests for the nested container scenarios
for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project.
In this article, I talk about the struggles to regain my confidence that I have been having
since my crash at the &lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/"&gt;end of May&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to let any readers of this article in on a little secret.  I do not
like reality television shows where people expect to get famous and do stupid things.
However, I do like reality shows where the show documents one or more interesting
aspects of work that gets done or where people are help each other.  Especially
if one of those two things are done in a weird or novel way, I am in!  Be it
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Jobs"&gt;Dirty Jobs&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt13833752/?ref_=ttfc_fc_tt"&gt;Backroad Truckers&lt;/a&gt;,
the way that the producers highlight the work always surprises me.  On the other
side of the coin, shows like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bar_Rescue"&gt;Bar Rescue&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restaurant:_Impossible"&gt;Restaurant Impossible&lt;/a&gt;
hit me in a separate way.  Part car crash, part counselling session, it is the
creative aspects of the hosts and how they try and resolve issues that appeal to
me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as much as I watch those shows as entertainment, in real life, I do take away
things from watching those shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="life-is-not-static"&gt;Life Is Not Static&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#life-is-not-static" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many things in life, I must monitor and adapt to the continually shifting
priorities that are an everyday part of my life.  If I do not do that, one or more parts of my
life suffers, with the underlying issue becoming more difficult to correct with each passing day.
While I have been able to keep my personal life and professional life relatively
well balanced in the last couple of months, it has come at the expense of my side-project
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balance in my personal and professional life is largely in part due to the
support I get from my wife and from the people that I work with.  Right now, my wife
and are I trying to figure out how to make
our house more “us”.  This includes equal parts thinking, trying things out, and just
doing the hard work.  Like any good science guy or engineer, I understand that
failure is not only an option, but it is an exceptionally good teacher.  While I hope for
things to work out on the first attempt, that is almost never the case.  With my
profession, I find that I am only as good as the people that I surround myself
with.  Having good people around me helps me elevate my game and keeps me motivated
to do my best. That and it keeps me on my toes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I must be brutally honest, I try and use only a bit of the positive
energy from one part of my life in the other parts of my life. That is not as much
wisdom on my part as it is a safety mechanism.  I can afford to siphon off a bit of
that energy, but I need to ensure that my focus and confidence in each area remains
at a healthy level for me to continue to succeed in life.  Due to
past experiences, I am extermely aware that what I just described as positive
energy and confidence can also apply to negative energy and a lack of confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back at May, the crash that happened was just a shopping cart looking for
a parked car.  Unless it was dealt with properly, it was an accident
that was inevitably going to happen.  Just like the opening acts of the reality
shows that I like watching, to anyone looking at that situation from the outside,
it was obvious that something needed fixing.  But in the moment, I was oblivious.
But due to the way I try and keep the parts of my life seperated, it was mainly
my side-project that suffered.  There was a bit of overlap, that was unavoidable.
But that well-earned wisdom helped me keep an even keel and not shake me up… too
much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I am approximately eight weeks past the crash, with most of the serious
stuff from the crash are now behind me.  Currently, my main personal project is to
slowly rework the backyard into something that is relaxing for my wife and I.  Due
to smaller successes and talking things through, I have confidence that we are
moving in a good direction.  In my professional life, I was tasked with doing a lot
of work on another project, with the team lead expressing his confidence in me based
on how he saw me handle small situations.  Based on that feedback and other pieces of
feedback at work, I am confident that I am going in a good direction at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my &lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project, it is a
slightly different story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard for me to admit this, especially to myself, but my confidence in the
project is not even close to where I want it to be.  Normally, I
stagger the work for the different parts of my life to make sure I am giving
each part what is needed for me to be happy and successful in that area.  While
I am getting what I need for the other parts of my life, I am struggling to get
to that same place with the PyMarkdown project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have explained before, that process that I take to author my articles is to
think about things and write down loose notes.  Borrowing from work, I call this
my ideation phase.  I usually write my ideation notes down in a very
technical manner or a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stream_of_consciousness"&gt;stream of consciousness&lt;/a&gt;
manner, and this week it was stream of consciousness manner. When I performed my
ideation exercise for this week’s article, as soon as I wrote down “confidence?”,
I put my pen down.  Seeing how I was writing the article, I decided to stare at it
for a while and just let it sink in.    The fact that I had
wrote down that word and followed it up with a question mark was a bit stunning
to me.  But as I thought about it more, I could not argue with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were little hints in my behavior that I had missed, but they were there.
In most of the cases, there were small things that I had chalked up to various
legitimate reasons.  What I had not noticed was that I was spending more focus
on those areas, which allowed me to succeed a bit more in those areas.  However,
those successes were at the expense of my side-project work.  Instead of doubling
down and focusing on getting debugging done, I was finding other stuff to do that
did not have to do with the project.  But why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After thinking about it for a couple of hours, I realized that I was scared. Over
my lifetime, there have been numerous times where I have come close to being
burnt out and at least one time where I burnt out.  When I really, deeply, and
honestly thought about it, I feared burning out.  The fact was, I had a
minor crash that I was able to recover from.  But instead of it being a fight to
get to the point where I crashed, it snuck up on me and ambushed me. Realistically,
I know that is not how it happened, but that is how I felt like it happened.
And bluntly, I was scared that it was going to happen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an old saying that “one bad apple can spoil the barrel.”  The meaning
behind that saying is that negative things can slowly pollute and degrade the
good things around them over time.  In this case, the negative thing was the
crash and the things to spoil was my confidence.  I got burned by the crash
and I have worked hard to deal with the main effects that happened due to the
crash.  Now that I have a good handle on those, it is time that I deal with
this piece of shrapnel and look for any other pieces that are lying around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do I deal with this lack of confidence in my work on the PyMarkdown
project?
Since these issues only came to me as I was writing this article, I sincerely do
not have an answer to the problem yet. I think that lack of an answer is
comforting to me because I would feel like I was being dishonest with myself
if I just came up with something that might work.  I would rather dedicate
time to think about how to increase my confidence while trying it
out on the project. Anything else would feel cheap and superficial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing my fingers for the next week. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="crashing"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting Back To Business?</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/28/getting-back-to-business/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-06-28:/2022/06/28/getting-back-to-business/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/14/still-recovering-from-the-crash/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how
my recovery from my crash was going.  In this article, I talk about how I am
getting back to work on my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you just need to unplug to get back to work.  That is what the last two …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/14/still-recovering-from-the-crash/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how
my recovery from my crash was going.  In this article, I talk about how I am
getting back to work on my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you just need to unplug to get back to work.  That is what the last two
weeks have been for me.  With some success and some failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="where-am-i-now"&gt;Where Am I Now?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#where-am-i-now" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my last article, I decided that I needed to take time off
to recover from my recent crash.  There were a handful of things that I had been
putting off around our house, and it was an opportune time to address them. The
fact that they had nothing to do with computers was a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came down to it, I just needed to shut down for a while.  I have been
pushing hard on my projects for months without a real break, and I was feeling
more of the disaster than the aster.&lt;sup id="fnref:YoungJustice"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:YoungJustice"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  On one hand, I knew that
I needed to take a break to make sure that I could recover properly and deal with
the anxiety that I have experience about my projects.  On the other hand, I was
just tired.  In looking back on that fateful weekend, I wonder if I was so
tired that I just pushed ahead “to get it done” without thinking of the ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, I sincerely believe it was the right move for me.  While the low
energy that I am feeling right now is mostly due to relaxing and working around
the house for the last two weeks, I can already feel it lifting bit-by-bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, I am pretty much at the end of what I have to say for this article.
Not much life related or project related that has changed in the last two weeks,
so nothing much to write about.  Next week?  Now I am hoping to have more to write
next week, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:YoungJustice"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am a fan of the Young Justice cartoon, which is where I heard “aster” for the first time. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:YoungJustice" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="crashing"></category></entry><entry><title>Still Recovering from the Crash</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/14/still-recovering-from-the-crash/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-06-14:/2022/06/14/still-recovering-from-the-crash/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/07/recovering-from-the-crash/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how I
was recovering from my recent crash while working on my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this article,
I talk about how things are going with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things for me about working on a side project is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/07/recovering-from-the-crash/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how I
was recovering from my recent crash while working on my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this article,
I talk about how things are going with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things for me about working on a side project is balancing
my project work with my home life and my professional life.  It is especially important
to order those three things in the correct order.  For me, that order is home life,
then professional life, then project work.  And when I do not keep that in mind,
I often get confused and place them in the wrong order.  A couple of weeks ago,
that is what happened, with bad results: a crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="where-am-i-today"&gt;Where Am I Today&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#where-am-i-today" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my &lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/07/recovering-from-the-crash/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;,
I am recovering from a crash from pushing work on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project.  As of today,
I feel that I am mostly back to where I was before the crash, but I am still feeling
a bit of the aftereffects of the crash.  For the most part, my mind and energy
levels are back to where they need to be. But my anxiety is another issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is that?  Because it was painful, and I have an anxiety disorder.  That is the
short answer.  The long answer is more detailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not shy about talking about having Autism, and I am not going to start now.
While my major diagnosis is Autism, I have minor diagnoses of Sensory Overload
Disorder and Autism-related Anxiety Disorder.&lt;sup id="fnref:note"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:note"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  What the first means is that a lot
of sensory input, such as being in a crowded restaurant, will overload me and cause
me to get exhausted very quickly.  This happens so often that my wife and I have our
own special code that I can use if the noise gets too much.  We have an agreement
that allows me to use that code without any downside. After more than ten years
with this code in place, I am finally starting to use it without feeling like I am
letting my wife down.  As this requires me to be in place that is noisy, I have
a great deal of control about when this hits me, allowing me to mitigate it very
effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anxiety Disorder is another story.  This is the fun one that I deal with on
a near daily basis.  Unlike a
normal person’s anxiety disorder, my disorder is tied to my ability to analyze
problems.  The issue that I have is that it is incredibly difficult for me to
not analyze things.  Basically, it is very hard to turn it off. That is one of
the reasons that music helps me concentrate when I do any mental work, be
it coding, writing, or thinking.  If I do not
have something “predictable” for my brain to latch on to, it starts to analyze
every bit of noise
around me, distracting me very quickly.  On the other hand, if I have music
that I normally listen to playing, I can jam and rock out without losing my train
of thought once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the absence of something to allow my mind to analyze at a low level, my
mind starts racing away from me.  While I have medicine and breathing techniques
to help with my anxiety, I still must do the work to find something to
counteract my anxiety.  And while certain techniques work most of the time,
nothing works all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anxiety-hurts"&gt;Anxiety Hurts&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#anxiety-hurts" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if everyone experiences anxiety in the same way that I do, but for
me, anxiety hurts.  Parts of my anxiety cloud my mind with analyses of what can
possibly happen. Most of the time, I can feel the anxiety as the slight tightening
of the muscles in my body, especially my chest.  Nothing serious, but I can easily feel my body
tensing up as if something terrible is coming.  Of course, I know that it is mostly
in my head. But in the moment, that knowledge tends not to help much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a purely mental point of view, feeling anxiety means that I miss
things with my family, my friends, and my environment.  Because my head is stuck
in a rut on whatever it is that is stressing me out, it means I cannot always focus my
time on what is around me.  And to be blunt, those things that I keep around me
are what really make my life worth living.  I know that movies are fun to watch,
and games are great to play, but it is the living things around me that help me
find satisfaction in life.  So not being able to focus on those things hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a more physical point of view, my anxiety tends to kick off my “fight-or-flight”
reflexes more than I would like them to.  Those extra hormones that are released
with those reflexes have side effects as well.  If my anxiety kicks off just before
I go to bed, it means I will have issues falling asleep or staying asleep, both of
which are not good.  If they kick off during the day, it can cause me to not be
able to focus on my tasks as well as I would like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the main physical side effect of my anxiety is on my energy levels.
Everything in life strives to find balance, and my energy levels are no exception.
When my anxiety kicks off my reflexes, I get a burst of energy that is almost
always inconvenient to deal with in the moment.  After the situation goes away,
I have the inverse problem: low energy.  As the anxiety focused my energy to
deal with “the crisis”, it is then followed by a lull while my body recharges.
Even with doctor prescribed medication to help mitigate these symptoms, it still
sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="keeping-things-low-key"&gt;Keeping Things Low-Key&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#keeping-things-low-key" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping that information in mind, I decided last week to take a low-key approach and
work on low priority items that have been on my to-do list of a long time.
From a code-clean point of view, I was never happy with the number of arguments
that I am passing around from function to function.  After thinking about it for
a couple of hours last week, I decided that this would be a good task to take
on while I am recovering.  Not a lot of thinking and not a lot of pressure.
Just clean refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that this work is not terribly important, that is why it is low-key. But
it is helping me clean things up in the project and giving me time to recover.
More importantly, it is helping me make progress with the project while not doing
anything too taxing.  And it is working.  It is taking time, but my anxiety is
slowly dissipating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushing myself to the point of crashing had lasting effects, and this
low key working is helping me fight the remaining side effect: my anxiety.
In trying to analyze why my anxiety is acting up, the best answer I can give
is this: my body does not want another crash.  I feel that this is going to
get better with more distance from that crash, but I just have to give my
mind and body the time that they need to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-thought-long-and-hard-about-this"&gt;I Thought Long And Hard About This&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#i-thought-long-and-hard-about-this" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with my anxiety still acting up from my crash, and the low key work helping to
get me back on track, I have decided that the best thing for me to do for a couple
of weeks is to take a break from my side projects and focus on non-mental projects
around the house.  I am not going to abandon my projects… I love working on them
too much!  But I know that if I want to be able to work on them with a clear mind,
I need to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, unless things change, back in a couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:note"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a psychologist or a medical doctor.  I have been formally diagnosed with these by a fully licensed psychologist who specializes in Autism.  The information presented here is from that diagnosis and is specific to me.  Please keep that in mind. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:note" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="crashing"></category></entry><entry><title>Recovering from the Crash</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/06/07/recovering-from-the-crash/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-06-07:/2022/06/07/recovering-from-the-crash/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how I
had suffered a major crash while working on my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this article,
I talk about continuing to battle those effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build up to last weekend was nasty.  After spending 30 months working on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how I
had suffered a major crash while working on my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this article,
I talk about continuing to battle those effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build up to last weekend was nasty.  After spending 30 months working on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project,
I do not believe I have ever had a time where I crashed as hard as I did that
weekend.  From that aspect of things, I was long overdue.  And now, I get
to deal with the long path to recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="one-size-does-not-fit-all"&gt;One Size Does Not Fit All&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#one-size-does-not-fit-all" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From over thirty years of professional experience, and even more experience working
on my own projects, I know that there are four level of crashing that I have encountered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="level-1-the-simple-crash"&gt;Level 1: The “Simple” Crash&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#level-1-the-simple-crash" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first level for me is the simple crash.  The reason I call this a “simple” crash is
because the path to get there is simple, the cause is simple, and the path to recover
is simple.  This is the crash that I tend to hit a lot, mostly because I like to push
myself a bit past what I am comfortable dealing with.  These
situations are when I am running out of energy when working outdoors or feel that
I need “just a little bit more” experimentation to get a problem solved.  The wonderful
thing about these situations is that the recovering from them is simple: relax and
take it easy.  A couple of hours with my feet up and watching a good movie and I
am ready to go again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the side effects are short term and are typically good for increasing stamina,
I am usually okay with these crashes.  I do watch out for their effects though,
making sure that the effects are not cumulative and do have a tangible benefit.
If not, I try and find a way to avoid the crash completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="level-2-the-eyes-wide-shut-crash"&gt;Level 2: The “Eyes Wide Shut” Crash&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#level-2-the-eyes-wide-shut-crash" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second level for me is the “eyes wide shut” crash. I tried to find another name for
this crash, but none of them had the same emphasis that I believe this name gives it.
While I do run into this physically on occasion, I run into this more with mental
problems through which I am working.  As much as it pains me to say it, this level
of crash is where the physical and mental damage starts to set in.  A good physical
example for me is going on a long hike after a dormant winter.  I can do the longer
hikes, but I must get back in shape first.  You know, make intelligent
decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is with those intelligent decisions that I get into the mental aspect of
this type of crash.  Telling myself “I can make it to the end” when I can see the
end of a hike is one thing.  Pushing myself regardless of the consequences when I
can still see the start is another thing entirely.  Mentally speaking, I get into
these situations when I do not pay attention to where I am at in solving a problem,
only telling myself that the problem must be solved.  However, instead of a sore
body from a hike, the damage is in my ability to solve other problems.  Instead
of thinking about the best approach, I just charge forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring this back to the name of the crash, it is as if I closed my eyes as hard
as I can, continuing to walk towards the end of the hike. Given that image, I
cannot see any way in which I would not harm myself.  Get lucky that it was not
a bad injury.  But at least minimal injuries are bound to occur.  And as these injuries are
a bit more severe than just the “simple” crash, the recovery is more prolonged.
For me, I need multiple days where I specifically focus on avoiding the areas
where the injuries occurred.  If I injure my legs from a hike, it means I sit down
with my legs raised.  Similarly, if I injure myself mentally, it means avoiding doing
the same type of work that I was doing that caused the injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to say that I do not crash like this frequently, but the best I can
do is to say that I do not crash like this as frequently as before.  There are
times where I push past the “simple” crash more than I should, and usually I
have a good reason for doing that.  But with these crashes, I am more
concerned about the injuries, mental and physical, and how they accumulate.
From my point of view, there usually is a good reason for pushing as far as I
did, but I know I am going to pay for it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="level-3-the-crossover-crash"&gt;Level 3: The “Crossover” Crash&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#level-3-the-crossover-crash" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third level that I have experienced is the “crossover” crash.  Once again, I spent time agonizing over
a good name for this crash before settled on this one.  The reason for that specific name is
hopefully self-evident.  When this type of crash occurs, it means I pushed through
the “eyes wide shut” crash to the point where any injuries crossed over from
the mental to the physical and vice versa.  While there are other ways to get to this
type of crash, such as getting into an automobile accident, I am going to focus
on those situations where I have a decent ability to affect the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that narrowed point of view, the best description is that I end up working
on something until I am sick of it.  I have not encountered this physically in
my life, but I have hit this mentally about ten times in my life.  In each case,
I pushed through the small injuries, weathering through the multiple, larger
injuries until I reached a breaking point.  Quite simply, I got to a point where
I just did not have any more left to give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my own nomenclature, this is where I ended up a week or so ago. My mind
was crashing so hard that I was feeling physical symptoms in my body.  And unlike
the recovery steps for the previous two situations, the steps to recovery for each
of these situations has been very specifically keyed to that situation.  For this last crash, I
had to immediately stop doing anything that did not feel right, which started out being most things.
For the first couple of days, even doing LEGO or watching some more interesting
movies was too much.  I just had to take it slow, evaluating where I am at each
day and adjusting for that.  Eventually I got to the point where I was able to
some debugging and writing of code, but I had to make sure to not push it too far.
And things did get better… just very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="level-4-burnout"&gt;Level 4: Burnout&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#level-4-burnout" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the level that nobody wants to be at: burnout.  I have been there once
in my life, and that was enough for me.  This is the crossover crash on
steroids.  When this hit me, my life energy just drained away from most of the
aspects of my life.  It was just nasty.  So nasty in fact, that I am just going
to say “seriously, do not get this far” and leave it at that.  It still hurts me
mentally to think back to that time.  And the recovery is just as brutal, taking
multiple weeks only to find myself back to the crossover crash stage and starting
my recover there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those were what I refer to as the “dark days.” That was a time in my life when I
really had no choice but to keep on pushing.  This was back in the 2002-2003 time
frame when the tech bubble had burst and there was hardly any work to be found anywhere.
So, when I did find contract work here and there, I worked myself to the bone.  There
were times where I was working on two full time contracts just to make ends meet.  It
was bad.  It was not a fun time for me or my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been there, I thought that there was nothing else I could do.  With twenty years
of experience since that year, I now understand that it may look like there were no
alternatives at the time, but there are always alternatives.  These were not the best
alternative, but they would have kept me from going through that dark time.  My advice
to any in a comparable situation is to please look for these alternatives, even if they
are not the best alternative, and achieve those alternatives.  Focus on the
things that mean a lot to you, which in my case is family.  Now, I do not really hate anyone,
and definitely do not have anyone that I would call an enemy, but as the saying
goes, “I wouldn’t want to wish that on my worst enemy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally recovered, I know I spent extra time with my family to make up for
wasting time with them when I was burned out.  Just do not go there. Find a way to
avoid going there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="where-am-i-at-now"&gt;Where Am I At Now?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#where-am-i-at-now" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, first off, I had to delay the publishing of this article by a day because I am
still recovering from that weekend. Normally the words for the articles just flow from
my fingers.  But that “flow” was just not there on
Sunday and Monday night.  On both nights, I pushed until I started feeling resistance
and then I backed off.  I decided that a good article a day late with a healthy mind
was better than adding extra time to my recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, the recovery is going well.  I am not at 100% yet, but I can see my own
progress in getting there.  I still took breaks this week and weekend while I was
working on fixing issues, but the frequency and duration of those breaks was noticeably
lower.  I also noticed that when I got to the point to take a break, it was more
of a nudge in my mind that I should stop, rather than any kind of yelling in my
ears.  So, while I am not back to where I was before that weekend, I can see that
happening in the next couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a project point of view… well, I honestly wish I had hit that brick wall sooner.
Before I crashed, I worked an entire weekend without making any headway on the
remaining container issues on which I was working.  As of this past Sunday afternoon,
all three groups of issues are debugged, fixed, and committed.  To be clear, while recovering
and not at full strength, I was able to solve those issues when a mostly healthy
me could not make a dent in those same issues over that fateful weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, that kind of information makes me feel humble. It helps me to
understand that I still have room to grow, especially when it comes to taking care
of myself.  One of my views on that information is: debugging and solving issues
is just as much about wisdom as it is about intelligence.  Brute force attacking
those issues just got me into a bad mental and physical state.  But a more
measured recovery attempt worked well, achieving my desired goals.  Sometimes,
all the pressure just gets in the way where a more measured and relaxed approach
works more seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not believe I am a good poster child for what to do when developing software
and testing that same software.  I am still learning, and I still on the journey
to be better.  But I do know that this experience has taught me to be more honest
with myself about debugging code and solving issues.  If not, then I can expect
another repeat of this in the future.  And though I do stupid things from time to
time, I would prefer to learn from them than repeat them.  It just seems easier
to me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="crashing"></category></entry><entry><title>Crashing On A Side Project</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2022-05-30:/2022/05/30/crashing-on-a-side-project/</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/17/markdown-linter-shifting-left/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I
talked about the work I have been doing in the background on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this
article, I talk about the effect that work had on me personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is a personal article. In addition, any longtime readers may notice that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2022/05/17/markdown-linter-shifting-left/"&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt;, I
talked about the work I have been doing in the background on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; project. In this
article, I talk about the effect that work had on me personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is a personal article. In addition, any longtime readers may notice that
this article was posted a week later than I usually post.  Basically, what happened
is that while working on my side projects last weekend, I crashed and crashed hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being my usual self, I thought it would be cool to try and help others avoid the
negativity of crashing and to help show the positives of taking care of one’s self
after such a crash.  Basically, how to avoid the pitfalls and help get on your
feet faster afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-crash-itself"&gt;The Crash Itself&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#the-crash-itself" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That weekend started like many other weekends I have spent working on my open
source projects.  I talked with my spouse and made sure that I had a clear idea of
what our schedule was like for the weekend, planning my project work around those
scheduled items.  Experience has taught me to include buffer time and extra “spouse”
time, so added that as well.  After that was all taken care of, I had a good idea
of the time I could spend on the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jackdewinter/pymarkdown"&gt;PyMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;
project and looked forward to clearing up some of the remaining issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, there are not that many issues left that I consider blocking issues,
but there are at least three issues that I believe meet that criteria.  Those issues
are all issues that were recorded during the addition of my latest round of container
combinations.  And as I am being honest, I will say this very bluntly: I was upset
with myself that I still had three issues left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not upset with myself for finding those issues.  Those issues were all good
finds due to the combinations.  What I was upset with is that it had been a good
couple of months since I found them, and they were still on the active issues list.
I temporarily forgot that I had a series of interview loops followed by on-boarding
at my new job.  And as I started locating those issues and dealing
with them, I slowly turned that weekend from a fun weekend improving the quality
of the project into a compulsive need to get those issues dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="how-did-it-happen"&gt;How Did It Happen?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#how-did-it-happen" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after a good eight days since it happened, most of what happened
that weekend is still clouded in my mind.  I know that initially I wanted to get
those issues dealt with, but I was forgiving with myself because of what had been
going on in my life.  But I also know that I had been trying to make headway
with those issues during the week, and I had not made any progress on any of those
three issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is where I think I started to descend into madness, so to speak.  While
I am usually forgiving with myself for life’s circumstances, I can be equally
unforgiving when I do not feel that I am making reasonable progress.  Put another
way, I wonder if I thought that I should have made more progress on those three
issues.  If so, then my lack of progress might have kicked off my anxiety and
then everything would have snowballed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-did-it-feel-like"&gt;What Did It Feel Like?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-did-it-feel-like" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The honest answer to the earlier question is: I can only guess.  I am not trying
to hide the truth, I honestly do not remember much of my work on that weekend.
I remember some stuff from Friday when I started working on debugging.  Project-wise,
I do not remember much until around 6PM on Sunday when I locked my computer and
buried my head
in my hands.  The little bits that I do remember between those two points are
filled with anger and frustration, and me trying to push past those to try and
get something done… and failing.  Not good memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember stopping at 6PM on Sunday with the intense feeling that I had pushed
myself too far.  The thought of unlocking my computer to start writing my weekly
article caused me to be nauseous. The thought of double checking my research from
the past two days to see if I missed something made me sick to my stomach.  I left
my computer locked, exited my office, and closed the door.  If the door had a
lock on it, I would have locked it as well. I was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just vegged out for the rest of the night, hoping to get a few of my brain cells back.
As long as I did not think about my project, I was fine.  I had some conversations
with my spouse, watched a couple of recorded Champion’s League matches, and
did work on one of my LEGO models.  My brain cells were all working in those areas.
As long as I mentally stayed away from the project, I was fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I went to work the next day, everything was fine there too. It was a good Monday
workwise, and I got a healthy amount of stuff done.  But the second I stopped
working and I went to my home computer, that sense of dread came back.  Reading
e-mail was fine, but anything more than that and that intense negative feeling just
crept back into my head.  I took until Wednesday before I was able to logon to that
computer to do something other than read e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="responding-to-my-crash-with-honesty"&gt;Responding To My Crash With Honesty&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#responding-to-my-crash-with-honesty" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could say that I was smart enough to avoid the crash in the first place, but
obviously I was not.  Because of the cloud around that entire weekend, I cannot
even take an honest look back at that time and figure out how to approach that
work differently.  I can guess, but that is all that it is, a guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been through situations like this over the years, the important part for
me was understanding that I had crashed and being honest with myself that I had
crashed.  This was not just a bad day or something that I would just “get over”,
it was a crash.  This was a negative situation that I knew I had to manage properly
if I wanted to recover quickly and with as few remnants hanging around as possible.
In lay terms, if I did not take care of myself properly, one or more of the
bad parts of this situation could say around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being honest with the little bit that I could remember, I was pretty sure that I
had pushed myself too far, too many times over that weekend.  Based on how I was
feeling on Sunday night, which was my best guess.
As such, I knew that I needed to avoid pushing myself for at least a week or so
until I started feeling better.  For me, that is a hard thing to do.  The only
thing driving my open source projects forward is me making the time and effort to
work on them.  As such, taking a break from any work like that is like nails on a
chalkboard for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that stopped me from doing that was my honesty with myself and my experience
with crashes in the past.  Based on that experience, even if I wanted to rush forward
to work on the projects, I knew that it was the wrong
thing to do in this case.  Forget about a little voice telling myself that it
was the wrong thing, it was a huge, booming, echoing voice.  That voice was telling
me that it was okay to evaluate myself for five or less minutes a day to see how I was
doing, but any more effort was going to be hurtful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I waited.  I tried each day to see how I was doing, but I waited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-then-the-recovery"&gt;And Then, The Recovery&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#and-then-the-recovery" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was the following Saturday morning before I evaluated myself for five minutes
without feeling decreased negative pressure. Assuming that I am usually able to
exert 100% effort, if I had to gauge where my energy or effort was at, then this
effort felt like it was in the 20-30% range.  It was not much, but it was a good start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using that level of effort, I started to work, taking decent breaks through
the rest of the day.  At any point, if I felt any pushback from myself, I simply
said “that is enough”, and walked away from the computer for at least an hour.
And through the course of the day, I must have done that around six times.
From a pure time point of view, it was not a good day for me working on the
PyMarkdown project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But from an effort point of view, it was encouraging.  By the end of that
Saturday, I would have to guess that I was more in the 45-55% range as far as
my effort was concerned.  More importantly, I had solved one of the issues that
had caused me to get into the negative situation in the first place.  It was
humbling.  What I had tried to do with each of the three remaining issues over
that nasty weekend, I had accomplished with less than half my usual effort while
I was recovering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news gets better.  Doing some more work yesterday, I was able to raise
my effort level to around 60-70%.  And while I did not solve either one of the
two remaining issues, I have been able to make substantial progress to get one
of them solved.  While I do not want to jinx anything, I am confident that with
more of the save level of work, I should be able to get that issue resolved
by the end of the week.  And if I do not get it done, I know I have to be easy
on myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="issues-for-thought"&gt;Issues For Thought&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#issues-for-thought" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a father and friend, I have tried to impart many small pieces of wisdom that
I have gained only though a lot of sacrifice. One of those bits of wisdom is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not matter how many times you get knocked down to your knees.  What matters
is how many times you decide to get up, dust yourself off, and try not to get
knocked down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all human beings, each of us in our own way.  And one of the unenviable
truths of being human is that we learn best from failure instead of success.  My
big failure was in not recognizing that I was in some form of a downward spiral
until I hit the bottom of that spiral.  But my success was in being truthful with
myself and acknowledging that I was at the bottom.  That success continued when I
concluded that I needed to take care of myself to get out of there.
It needed to be my choice to dust myself off after getting knocked down, and no
one else’s. And while it was not any easy choice, I believe it was the right choice
to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, in a typical “me” move, instead of focusing on the fact that I crashed,
I decided to share my experience and try and to figure out how to grow from it.
It took me over twenty years to learn this particular pattern… I hope I can
help shortcut some of that time for others.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="crashing"></category></entry><entry><title>The Inspiration For Jack's Digital Workbench</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/11/15/the-inspiration-for-jacks-digital-workbench/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-11-15:/2019/11/15/the-inspiration-for-jacks-digital-workbench/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Growing up in the late 70s and early 80s, the only computers that were available to me
at the time were the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodore_PET"&gt;Commodore&lt;/a&gt; line of
computers locked up in schools.  To feed my growing and inquiring mind, that left
electronics and mechanics to experiment with, and expendable examples of both …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Growing up in the late 70s and early 80s, the only computers that were available to me
at the time were the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodore_PET"&gt;Commodore&lt;/a&gt; line of
computers locked up in schools.  To feed my growing and inquiring mind, that left
electronics and mechanics to experiment with, and expendable examples of both were hard
to come by.  My only choice was to scrounge around for things in various stages of
disrepair, and upon getting one of those uncommon finds, take it downstairs to our
unheated garage and trying to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; it.  Far from a stellar place to work, it was not
heated, not ventilated and rarely keep clean.  And at the head of that garage, on the
wall adjoining the basement, was a solitary, ugly workbench fastened to the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That workbench was often the birthplace of many far-fetched dreams of what I could do if
only I could properly figure the thing laid out before me.  I almost never had the right
tools, so to be totally honest, more things got &amp;ldquo;more broken&amp;rdquo; than ever got fixed or
reassembled into something else.  Even with the right tools, while I believe my ability
to make it work again would have increased, the drive and knowledge to do so was
probably not there.  But even with a veritable graveyard of things that were not
completed, I chose not to dwell on the failures or make excuses for why I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish
them.  Instead, every time I approached that bench, I chose to dream and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I fondly remember the times I stood at that bench with the single, bright
work light in my eyes.  Back then, it was always the journey and the creative
imagination that was important.  The only pressure to produce something concrete was
when my mom asked &amp;ldquo;So, what have you been working on?&amp;rdquo;  However, as I grew older, I
realized that my mom&amp;rsquo;s question was equal parts sincere interest on her part and her
desire to have me grow past that graveyard of unfinished projects.  I believe that she
wanted me to be able to channel that creativity into the something tangible. Not so she
could show off my work to others, but in a sincere effort to help me grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are a lot different some 40 years later.  Even though I longer use that old
workbench, I try and capture a lot of that creativity and wonder on a daily basis, both
in my professional life and home life.  The projects I undertake are no longer
far-fetched, but grounded in reality.  As a result, I am better at selecting the projects
that I want to work on and I am more successful in carrying them to completion.
When a project fails, I embrace one of the Mythbuster&amp;rsquo;s idioms,
&lt;a href="https://mygeekwisdom.com/2016/01/09/failure-is-always-an-option/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Failure is always an option&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
and try and learn what failed and how to deal with it next time.  While a small number of
projects till end up in my project graveyard, but I keep the larger number of successful
projects on proud display in my workplace and my house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why start a blog and call it &amp;ldquo;Jack&amp;rsquo;s Digital Workbench&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple answer is that I started blogging to help me keep a digital form of that
garage workbench alive and renewed.  I want to inspire people in the same way that my
mother has done in the past and continues to do so today.  I want to inspire people to
dream big, following each dream up with a grounding that enables them to work on that
project and gain confidence in their skills along the way.  I want to inspire people to
try and take something on, taking any failures along the way as teaching or learning
moments and not as dream killers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, the reason for Jack&amp;rsquo;s Digital Workbench is to communicate with others and to
inspire them in a positive manner to allow them to, in turn, inspire the people around
them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Embracing Something Hard</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/08/18/embracing-something-hard/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-08-18:/2019/08/18/embracing-something-hard/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look at my &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jackdewinter/"&gt;LinkedIn profile&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll
see that I have been around for a while.  I was a Software Developer for many years
beginning in 1991 at a small 2 person company in Waterloo,  until a stint in Denmark
gave me a bit of a wakeup call …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look at my &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jackdewinter/"&gt;LinkedIn profile&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll
see that I have been around for a while.  I was a Software Developer for many years
beginning in 1991 at a small 2 person company in Waterloo,  until a stint in Denmark
gave me a bit of a wakeup call.  When I came back to the United States in January 2011, I
changed from a Software Developer to a Software Developer in Test.&lt;sup id="fnref:SDET"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:SDET"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  While I started my
career &amp;ldquo;making things that work&amp;rdquo;, after 20 years I was more focused on &amp;ldquo;making things work
better.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That career change was a wonderful and happy change for myself that I have never looked back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be specific, I am not a tester.  I do know a lot about testing, but that is not my primary
focus.  My focus is looking at interconnected systems and figuring out how to improve them.
It is not about breaking things, like a lot of people assume, but making the team around me
better.  It is about standing up and mentioning that having 5 developers struggle through the
same setup process for 4 days each is just plain inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is about standing up and mentioning that having 5 developers struggle through the same
setup process for 4 days each is just plain inefficient.  Solution: Add a responsibility for
documenting the setup process for the first person, with each subsequent person responsible for
the process of updating the document to current standards.  Benefits: The team owns the
process and its updating, with a clear path of responsibility if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work the next time
it is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is about looking holistically at a group of systems and, while developers enjoy being
creative,  focusing that creativity on the parts of the systems that will benefit them and the
team the most.  Solution: Use templates and common libraries where possible to reduce the
amount of &amp;ldquo;creativity&amp;rdquo; needed for anything remotely common to as close to zero as possible.
Benefits: The team spends time on stuff that needs to be solved and not stuff that has already
been solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is about asking each member of the team what they expect of documentation from the
projects that their projects rely on.  Solution: Setup a set of &amp;ldquo;how-to&amp;rdquo; guides that documents
common practices for the documentation of projects for the team, hopefully with a &amp;ldquo;dummy&amp;rdquo;
project that gives a live interpretation of those guides.  Benefits:  The team writes a set
of documentation for their systems that looks like they were written by the same team, instead
of a mish-mash of people thrown together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My job is as much about asking the simple but tough questions, as it is about having an idea
on how to respond to both the questions and answers that follow those tough questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual job is almost always about automation or process, it almost always involves changing
the way people look at things, and unfortunately it almost always includes having someone&amp;rsquo;s ego
bruised along the way.  Partially due to me having Autism, I can see certain patterns very
easily, almost as if I was reading a book.  Changing the way developers look at things almost
always brings around the bruised egos.  A lot of developers associate code they write with
themselves.  As such, saying that the code or process can be improved becomes confused with
saying that the developers themselves can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, when that happens, it is often the people asking the questions and making
suggestions on how to make things better that take the brunt of the anger that results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still remember my daughter asking me one time why I liked being a software developer in test,
as I am often frustrated with people over a perceived lack of momentum.  Thinking about it
quickly, the immediate answer was easy: I am good at a decent portion of it.  If you are in a
box and looking around you, all you see is the box.  I am able to elevate my perspective to a
higher level and not only see the one box, but the boxes around it.  I can see how they are
stacked, and if they are looking like they will tip over.  That came second nature to me. But
it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the complete answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as I responded with that answer to my daughter, there was something
missing in that answer, and it bothered me when I thought about that conversation over the next
couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was years later during one of those teaching moments we as parents have with our children
that it occurred to me.  I was reminding one of my children that we have a saying in our
family: being knocked flat on your ass is not the last step, it&amp;rsquo;s just the step before we pick
ourselves up, brush ourselves off, and try again.  Yeah, having issues and making mistakes
sucks, but they helped make us who we are, and it&amp;rsquo;s how we stand up again that defines us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was then that I realized: I became a software developer in test because it was hard.  I
wanted the challenge to make things better, and to help others get better at what they were
doing.  I knew I was going to encounter stubborn people along the way, but I was determined
that I would try and figure out a way to get through to them.  Sure, I get knocked flat on my
rear end a fair number of times, but I always get back up and try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just the other people, it was myself.  I had to learn when to strive for
perfection and when to strive for &amp;ldquo;just good enough&amp;rdquo;.  I had to learn to find the balance
between what I felt was the right decision and what the right decision was for the business
right now.  I had to learn that while my own passion and vision were wonderful, unless I was
able to share those things in a way that others were receptive to, they meant nothing.  I
had to learn to get in a state of continuous learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that time, I finally had my answer: I liked being a Software Developer in Test
because I was good at it and because it was a hard challenge that forced me to learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That takes me to the last couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I have wanted to start my own blog and help out an open source project.  I was
under no illusion that either objective was going to be easy, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t have a clue about
how different it would evolve into from what I thought it originally was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was going through and picking out a platform for my blog, I kept notes and started to
turn them into articles.  That was relatively easy.  Or at least the first pass was.  I found
out that when it comes to articles, I want to make sure I am saying the right thing in the
right way, and can literally spend 45 minutes working on one sentence.   Shortly after that,
I also learned that I can spend 5 minutes getting said sentence in a way that makes sense,
add text a marker like &lt;code&gt;**TBD**&lt;/code&gt; before it, and then come back to it at the end of the article.
And yes, following that, I realized that about half the time, going downstairs and doing
something totally unrelated caused me to think of &lt;strong&gt;THE EXACT&lt;/strong&gt; phrase that I needed within
seconds of coming back after the break.  Yup, learning is fun, and hindsight is perfect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog isn&amp;rsquo;t hard in terms of writing for me, but the production of it sometimes gets me.
If you want to stay on track, you have to give yourself some kind of schedule.  For me it
was to publish once a week on something technical.  It is a challenge to always make sure you
have a couple of articles on the go at any time, and that you can polish one up and
publish it on a weekly basis.  I also have to balance the writing with exploring stuff so that
I can write about it in my blog.  And I realized I have to extend that out 4-6 weeks to give
me time to go through a good ideation process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In picking a theme for my website, my attention was drawn to the Elegant theme for its
simplicity and crispness.  Looking into the documentation a bit, I noticed that some things
were close, but not spot on.  I wanted to get one of those features working for my website,
so asking for some help getting it working, I changed the document to better document what
needed to be done.  The change was welcomed, and I volunteered to help out with any other
articles.  That is how I started contributing to the Elegant theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it entail?  Take the work I am doing for my blog articles, subtract the subject
matter research, in certain cases add some localized research, and supplement that with making
sure I write the articles in a more professional and international. &lt;sup id="fnref:International-Tone"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:International-Tone"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
On top of that, apply a bit of my developer in test training and try and make sure I have a
solid theme, and that I am making the process easier for me and other users of Elegant in the
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For sure, doing these things at the same time can be nuts, but I am thoroughly enjoying the
challenge.  I am growing both personally and professionally as I work though things on each
project, some inside of my expertise and some outside of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I wish there were more hours in the day, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t trade the learning I am doing
for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it&amp;rsquo;s quite often hard, but it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be worth it if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard,
would it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:SDET"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, where I currently live, I am a Software Development Engineer in Test or SDET.  I do not have an engineering degree.  In any other country, including my native Canada, I am a Software Developer in Test or SDT.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:SDET" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:International-Tone"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will probably write an upcoming article about this to explain it fully.  In essence, if you are writing in English for an international audience, you have to remember that a fair percentage of your readers are not native English speakers.  Until they reach a point in their English proficiency, they will typically think in their native language and translate what they are reading from English to that native language.  As such, you want to keep your language as free from idioms and imprecision as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:International-Tone" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Personal"></category><category term="trying your best"></category><category term="trying something new"></category><category term="teachable moments"></category><category term="what are SDETs"></category><category term="teaching software quality"></category></entry></feed>