<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jack's Web Site - Technology</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jackdewinter.github.io/</id><updated>2019-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Choosing a Static (Web) Site Generator</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/08/04/choosing-a-static-web-site-generator/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-08-04:/2019/08/04/choosing-a-static-web-site-generator/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first article in a series about setting up my own web site using a
Static Site Generator.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Static Site Generators” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first article in a series about setting up my own web site using a
Static Site Generator.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Static Site Generators” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I want a static web site?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been on my mind for a couple of years that I would like to talk about some of the
things that I find cool and other things that I feel strongly about.  As a big proponent of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servant_leadership"&gt;servant leadership&lt;/a&gt;, I want to help and
inspire people to do more, be more, and help more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, I want a low-friction, easy to use platform that allows me to communicate with and
help others in my own way.  I also want tooling and workflows to be efficient so that I can
spend more time communicating and less time fidgeting on the web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, I want to focus on something that is simple, but extensible.  I want to be able
to have a good mix of my own pages and a blog, allowing for flexibility on what I am doing. I
want to be able to focus on the message and my voice, rather than the medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my research, Static Site Generators fulfils those requirements in spades.  But as with
a number of things I do, I want to take the time to determine if they are the right choice
for my web site, and if so, select the right one for me.  I would rather take a small
amount of time now to ensure it is a good fit, than to take time reworking things because it
wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-static-site-generators"&gt;What are Static Site Generators?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-are-static-site-generators" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static Site Generators (SSGs) are programs that take a certain type of web site and shift
the heavy loading of the web site from the content-request point to the content-update point.
Put another way, the decision of what content to show the viewer of the web page is changed
from when the web page is requested by the browser to when the web page content is updated by
the author.  Therefore, to be eligible to use a SSG for a given web site, that web site must
have all its content available when the content is updated, with no real time content
present.  There are small ways to get around that restriction, but those present their own
challenges.  As such, I am going to assume that 95% of the web site is going to be static, and
that all the important information is within that 95%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSGs themselves usually combine different technologies to achieve their results: writing,
templating/styling, metadata, and publishing.  The pages for the site need to be written in
either a supplied WYSIWYG editor or in some format like Markdown.  Once the pages are written,
generic styling and templating are applied to the collection of pages to make sure that the
branding on the pages is consistent.  To help organize the pages, most SSGs include some form
of metadata that is attached to the pages, used by the SSG to group pages and provide other
guidance to the SSG itself.  Finally, when the pages are checked over, there needs to be a
simple way to publish them to the intended web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducing the barrier to entry and keeping it low is essential to a SSGs success.  Therefore
providing multiple technology choices for parts of the SSG is common.  All the SSGs that I
looked at had a variety of options for most of these technologies, with templating and styling
being the exception. In the case of templating, most of the SSGs support a single default
templating engine that is used on all the pages.  With respect to styling, common HTML
technologies such as Cascading Style Sheets (CSSs) are most commonly used.  Besides keeping
the cost of the templating and styling low, using a common technology allows for lots of
examples to be provided by the Internet at a low cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="is-a-static-site-generator-the-right-choice-for-me"&gt;Is a Static Site Generator The Right Choice For Me?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#is-a-static-site-generator-the-right-choice-for-me" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In determining whether SSGs are the right technology for my site, I started making a list of
the things I was primarily worried about with a web site:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I deal with security concerns at work, this one was top of mind.  How often have I
heard about various platforms and websites being hacked in the last month?  To avoid this,
I want to keep my web site as simple as possible.  Static pages created by a SSG leave a
single attack vector: the repository where my website’s HTML pages are being stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitigating attacks by only having a single attack vector is very attractive solution for
me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ease Of Use&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to be messing with the web site more than I have to.  I either want to be
updating something on the site in response to something I am working on, or working on that
thing. I am already used to writing documentation at work in Markdown, so writing web
pages in Markdown is already very efficient for me.  In a similar manner, at work I keep
documentation in a version control system, so keeping the pages in their various stages of
completion in a readable form in version control is also efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using my already existing workflows, with minor modifications, is an acceptable
solution that keeps ease of use high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real-Time Contents and User Input&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of my focus at work is making sure that we can anticipate and plan for events that
happen to change our system’s state.  If a user or another system sends a request to our
system, can we validate the request, verify the system is in a good state for the request,
and enforce the correct behavior for the response?  Any good SSG takes care of this issue
by eliminating any change of state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolving the concerns of state management by removing all state information seems like an
ideal solution for the limited scope of my personal web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once those were out of the way, only the big question remained:  Do I have any plans for a web
site that would require it to support dynamic content?  My primary purpose is to allow me
to communicate to interested readers.  As such, the sites’s content is largely going to
change only when I write something new and publish it.  Based on the 95% barrier I set for
myself above, such content appears to be will within that barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To handle the remaining 5%, I am fine with any dynamic content for my site being generated
using JavaScript.  A good example of that is using something like &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;
for dynamic comments.  By handling such things with a Javascript approach, I can keep the
simple things simple, only making things more complex when they need to be.  To me, that seems
to be a solid way to handle the few exceptions that may arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those reasons, I believe an SSG is an ideal choice for a personal web site with a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="which-one-to-choose"&gt;Which One to Choose?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#which-one-to-choose" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case I need or want to do any extension work, I want the SSG to be in a language I am
comfortable with, maintaining the ease of use concern from the previous section.  At the
moment, that limits the SSG language to C#, Java, and Python.  While I can work effectively in
other languages, the comfort and enjoyment levels are not there.  As I am doing this for
myself, I want the writing of any extensions to be easy and fun to increase the chances that I
will stick with the writing and the SSG choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at a number of sites, these are the SSGs that appear the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Generator&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Language&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Website&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Last Updated&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hugo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Go&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/"&gt;https://gohugo.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;May 30, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pelican&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Python&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;http://blog.getpelican.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;May 13, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hexo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Node.js&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://hexo.io/"&gt;https://hexo.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jun 6, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jekyll&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ruby&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;http://jekyllrb.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jun 9, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gatsby&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NodeJs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/gatsbyjs"&gt;https://github.com/gatsbyjs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jun 9, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that the last updated column is current as of 2019-Jun-09.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these goals in mind, I looked through the choices for static site generators and decided
to go with Pelican.  It’s written in Python, has been maintained recently, any extensions are
written in Python, and seems to be easy to use.  This choice supports my desire to write pages
and articles in Markdown, and any needed extensions can be tweaked if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-accomplished"&gt;What Was Accomplished&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-was-accomplished" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of this article, I was intrigued by Static Site Generators and whether or not
SSGs would be an effective tool for me to communicate through.  During the article, I not
only determined that it was the right fit, but selected the Pelican as the SSG to use, based
on its Python coding and recent updating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that this determination to use SSGs, and Pelican specifically, puts me in a good
position to start building my web site with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="if-you-are-trying-to-decide"&gt;If You Are Trying To Decide…&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#if-you-are-trying-to-decide" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are trying to decide if SSGs, or a specific SSG, will work for you and your site,
I would encourage you to walk through a similar process to what I did.  Figure out your own
concerns for your own web site, and determine whether or not an SSG will address those
concerns.  If you think you may write extension for it, take a look at the language of the SSG
and make sure you are familiar with the extension language.  Most importantly, figure out
whether your choice of SSGs in general or a specific SSG will serve as a tool for you to
publish your information, or whether it will be an impediment to you publishing.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the point where I was at when I made the decision, Pelican appeared to be a good choice
for me.  I did some research to make sure this was the right choice for me.  Make sure you
ask yourself those questions, get those answers through research, and make sure your choice
is going to work for you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next"&gt;What’s Next?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#whats-next" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I need to start exploring Pelican and how to set it up with default content.  This will
be covered in the next post Setting Up the Pelican Static Site Generator.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="static website generator"></category><category term="static site generator"></category><category term="websites"></category></entry><entry><title>Glanceable Displays: Fine Tuning A Raspberry Pi Installation</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/28/glanceable-displays-fine-tuning-a-raspberry-pi-installation/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-07-28:/2019/07/28/glanceable-displays-fine-tuning-a-raspberry-pi-installation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the third article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/"&gt;previous …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the third article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt;,
I detailed the steps required to get the Raspbian (Linux) operating system installed on a
Raspberry Pi with remote access through
SSH enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article attempts to move the needle forward by tackling a number of the issues that I had
in getting necessary foundation services up and running on my Raspberry Pi.  The two services
that I had issues with were: ensuring that Wi-Fi was working properly and that the Raspberry
Pi clock was being set properly.  Until I was confident that these two issues were resolved,
I was not confident that I would be able to use my glanceable display in it’s intended
location, as that location does not have any wired network access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the steps in the previous article concluded with providing SSH access to the Raspberry Pi, I performed all of the following configuration using an SSH client.  While you are welcome to enter them through a keyboard directly connected to the Raspberry Pi, I did not test any of the steps in that manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the experience of reviewing and retrying these steps, &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt; is a good friend. If it looks like something didn’t work and you think it should, consider using &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt; to reboot the machine and carry on from there.  This is very handy when changing configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-1-wi-fi-access"&gt;Step 1: Wi-Fi Access&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1-wi-fi-access" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you have the fortune of having a wired network outlet available near your display AND
enjoy the aesthetic of having a network cable going into your display, you most likely want
to use Wi-Fi to access your display.  Here are the steps I went though to get wireless access
enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-1a-searching-for-existing-wireless-access"&gt;Step 1a: Searching for Existing Wireless Access&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1a-searching-for-existing-wireless-access" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first command that I used to check for wireless network access was the &lt;code&gt;ifconfig&lt;/code&gt; command.
This is a general command used to determine what network connections are available.   I had a
network cable running into the machine, but nothing else, so the following response&lt;sup id="fnref:ellipses"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ellipses"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
was expected:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;eth0: flags=4163&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,RUNNING,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        ...
lo: flags=73&amp;lt;UP,LOOPBACK,RUNNING&amp;gt;  mtu 65536
        ...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it looks like gibberish to some, it was what I expected.  Linux systems often use the
tag &lt;code&gt;eth0&lt;/code&gt; for the first wired connection and the tag &lt;code&gt;lo&lt;/code&gt; for the loopback connection.  The
important thing I noticed was that I didn’t see a &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt; tag, typically used for the first
wireless connection.  The clear observation I had was that the system did not currently have
a capability to have a wireless connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This observation on a normal computer running Linux might be farfetched, but from information
gained researching the Raspberry Pi on various forums, it is relatively normal for a Raspberry
Pi to not have any wireless capability built-in.  As wireless components have recently become
cheaper, it seems like it is only the latest versions of the Raspberry Pi 3 have wireless
access built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not repeated these steps on a newer Raspberry Pi, but I would expect that doing so would allow me to skip the next section on installing the adapter.  I will update the article once I have tested that scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-1b-installing-a-wireless-adapter"&gt;Step 1b: Installing a Wireless Adapter&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1b-installing-a-wireless-adapter" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my instance, the machine I was configuring did not have any wireless capabilities built in.
That was resolved in short order by noting down the connection requirements for the household
router (WPA2-PSK (AES)) and purchasing an inexpensive USB Wi-Fi adapter from a nearby store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If possible, use that store’s online presence to inspect the possible adapters, verifying 1-3 choices for adapters that meet the router’s specifications.  While not necessary, it can avoid round trips to the store to try and find the right adapter.  Doing this, I found that my local store had a TP-Link TL WN823N USB Adapter that was right for the job for $15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning home from the store with an inexpensive TP-Link TL WN823N adapter, I powered off the
Raspberry Pi, installed the Wi-Fi adapter in one of the open USB slots, and powered up the
Raspberry Pi.  Once Raspbian had booted up, I reconnected to the machine using SSH and entered
the &lt;code&gt;lsusb&lt;/code&gt; command.  This command is similar to the &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command to list files, but is used
to list various USB components that the machine has recognized.  The response I received from
that command was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Bus 001 Device 006: ID 2357:0109 TP-Link TL WN823N RTL8192EU
Bus 001 Device 005: ID 0461:4e26 Primax Electronics, Ltd
Bus 001 Device 004: ID 0461:4d64 Primax Electronics, Ltd
Bus 001 Device 003: ID 0424:ec00 Standard Microsystems Corp. SMSC9512/9514 Fast Ethernet Adapter
Bus 001 Device 002: ID 0424:9514 Standard Microsystems Corp. SMC9514 Hub
Bus 001 Device 001: ID 1d6b:0002 Linux Foundation 2.0 root hub
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as the adapter I bought was a TP-Link TL WN823N, I was relieved to see it listed as
device 06.  At this point it was clear to me that the Raspberry Pi recognized the adapter, and
it was time to install the required drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-1c-installing-the-wi-fi-drivers"&gt;Step 1c: Installing the Wi-Fi Drivers&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1c-installing-the-wi-fi-drivers" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a research point of view, this was the most frustrating part of getting wireless access
working.  In most of the articles I researched, the authors seemed to assume that the drivers
for a given adapter would already be installed in the Raspbian distribution.  The few articles
I found that handled missing drivers were very specific, and not very helpful.  They often
used the Raspbian &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; family of commands to look for an adapter, and each adapter
I found seemed to have a slightly different way of making sure it worked properly.  As I
was writing down notes to help other people, that experience was far from helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything changed when my research led me to a reference to the
&lt;a href="https://www.umpah.net/raspberry-pi-security-cam-installing-motioneye/"&gt;Fars Robotics&lt;/a&gt;
driver install script.  This breaks down the process into the following three commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo wget http://www.fars-robotics.net/install-wifi -O /usr/bin/install-wifi
sudo chmod +x /usr/bin/install-wifi
sudo /usr/bin/install-wifi
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of playing around with &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; commands and looking for a specific driver, this
script automated the process, finding the correct driver and installing it.  The commands
first download the script into the &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt; directory, set it to be executable, and then
execute the script.  Within 60 seconds, it had completed, and it’s output suggested that the
driver for my TP-Link TL WN823N had installed successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To double check that it worked properly, I resubmitted the &lt;code&gt;ifconfig&lt;/code&gt; command and got the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;eth0: flags=4163&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,RUNNING,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        inet 192.168.2.3  netmask 255.255.255.0  broadcast 192.168.2.255
        ...
lo: flags=73&amp;lt;UP,LOOPBACK,RUNNING&amp;gt;  mtu 65536
        inet 127.0.0.1  netmask 255.0.0.0
        ...
wlan0: flags=4163&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,RUNNING,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        ...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great!  Progress!  The new Wi-Fi adapter was installed, the driver was connected, and Raspbian
was reporting that it could talk with it!  From experience, I now had to configure the machine
to connect to the wireless network.  From the output, this was somewhat obvious.  For the
&lt;code&gt;eth0&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lo&lt;/code&gt; adapters, there was a line beginning with &lt;code&gt;inet&lt;/code&gt; that described the current
IPv4 setup for that adapter.  As the &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt; adapter was missing the &lt;code&gt;inet&lt;/code&gt; line (and also the
&lt;code&gt;inet6&lt;/code&gt; line), Raspbian could talk to the adapter, but the adapter was not connected to the
local Wi-Fi network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, configuring Wi-Fi access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-1d-configuring-wi-fi-access"&gt;Step 1d: Configuring Wi-Fi Access&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1d-configuring-wi-fi-access" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the previous section on Installing the Wi-Fi Drivers, I found many articles on how
to do this by hand, each with its own little twist on how to set things up better.  In my case,
I wanted to go for repeatable and easy, and the &lt;code&gt;sudo raspi-config&lt;/code&gt; command used
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/#step-5-setting-up-ssh-access"&gt;to set up SSH access&lt;/a&gt;
proved to be the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the main menu, I selected &lt;code&gt;2 network options&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;N2 WiFi&lt;/code&gt;.  As it was my first time
setting up the network on this machine, I was prompted for my country, which I entered.  Next I
was prompted with &lt;code&gt;Please enter SSID&lt;/code&gt;, and I responded with my router’s SSID.  This was
followed with the inevitable &lt;code&gt;Please enter passphrase.  Leave it empty if none.&lt;/code&gt;, to which I
responded with my router’s password.  Hoping everything would work out, I pressed the &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt;
button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After waiting for approximately 30 seconds, focus was returned to the main configuration
screen.  Exiting out of that screen and back to the main screen, executing the &lt;code&gt;ifconfig&lt;/code&gt; now
had the following response:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;eth0: flags=4099&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        inet 192.168.2.3  netmask 255.255.255.0  broadcast 192.168.2.255
        ...
lo: flags=73&amp;lt;UP,LOOPBACK,RUNNING&amp;gt;  mtu 65536
        inet 127.0.0.1  netmask 255.0.0.0
        ...
wlan0: flags=4163&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,RUNNING,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        inet 192.168.2.67  netmask 255.255.255.0  broadcast 192.168.2.255
        ...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was what I was waiting for!  At the moment, the &lt;code&gt;eth0&lt;/code&gt; wired connection had an address of
192.168.2.3 and the &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt; wireless connection had an address of 192.168.2.67.  The address
192.168.2.3 is the one I had been SSHing into while fixing up the Wi-Fi, so that lined up.
Based on my router’s configuration, 192.168.2.67 was a likely address for a new machine, so
that lined up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have your wireless network secured, make sure you follow the normal steps for adding a new machine to your network.  In my case, forgetting my normal steps cost me over an hour trying to figure out why the Raspberry Pi would not connect to the network!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To verify things were working, I repeated the relevant portions of
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/#step-5-setting-up-ssh-access"&gt;Step 5: Setting Up SSH Access&lt;/a&gt;
from the previous article, using the new address 192.168.2.67, instead of the old one
192.168.2.3.  Once this succeeded, the final test was to disconnect the physical connection and
see if the wireless connection worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did take a lengthy bit of time, and one trip to a local store for hardware, but it was
very gratifying being able to talk to the glanceable display over a wireless connection!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-2-system-clock-synchronization"&gt;Step 2: System Clock Synchronization&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2-system-clock-synchronization" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Raspberry Pi is a useful little machine, it’s small form causes it to not have a
component that many machine take for granted: a system clock.  Not having this set up for your
glanceable display can cause any display of time to be extremely off.  In addition,
if the Raspberry Pi’s time is not decently close to the actual time, the downloading of extra
components through mechanisms such as the &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; commands may fail.  To avoid these issues,
setting up proper system clock synchronization is a must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2a-installing-the-ntp-service"&gt;Step 2a: Installing the NTP Service&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2a-installing-the-ntp-service" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quickest and most efficient solution to solve the synchronization issue was to install the
NTP time service.  In the distribution of Raspbian that I was using, the NTP service was not
installed.  When I entered the command &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl status ntp&lt;/code&gt;, I saw the following
output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Unit ntp.service could not be found.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on various articles, the clear solution was to install the NTP service using &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt;
with the following command: &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install ntp&lt;/code&gt;.  Once that finished, when I repeated
the &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl status ntp&lt;/code&gt; command, I then received the following output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;● ntp.service - Network Time Service
   Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/ntp.service; enabled; vendor preset: enabled)
   Active: active (running) since ...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I was satisfied that the NTP service was up and running, but not that it was
working correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2b-diagnosing-the-ntp-service-configuration"&gt;Step 2b: Diagnosing the NTP Service Configuration&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2b-diagnosing-the-ntp-service-configuration" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the service was loaded, I needed to confirm that the NTP service was working properly.
The easy way to do this was to reboot the machine using &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt; and then use the
&lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt; command to check the date.  When I followed that pattern, the date was over 2 weeks
off from the actual time.  Time to go into debug mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation on the NTP service mentions a useful command: &lt;code&gt;ntpq -p&lt;/code&gt;.  This command
lists information about what the current NTP service is doing.   Presented as a series of
columns, the important column was the number of seconds since the service successfully
contacted a specific NTP server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I checked the output of the command, I was greeted with the following table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;     remote           refid      st t when poll reach   delay   offset  jitter
==============================================================================
 0.debian.pool.n .POOL.          16 p    -   64    0    0.000    0.000   0.004
 1.debian.pool.n .POOL.          16 p    -   64    0    0.000    0.000   0.004
 2.debian.pool.n .POOL.          16 p    -   64    0    0.000    0.000   0.004
 3.debian.pool.n .POOL.          16 p    -   64    0    0.000    0.000   0.004
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the when column, the issue seemed to be that it was not able to connect to those
servers and get information about them.  Doing a bit of research, it turned out that other
people have had problems with the default servers for the NTP server, and there were ways
to address that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2c-changing-the-ntp-service-configuration"&gt;Step 2c: Changing the NTP Service Configuration&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2c-changing-the-ntp-service-configuration" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I had the NTP service installed and had issues with the default configuration, it
was time to look at it.  The configuration for the service is located in the file
&lt;code&gt;/etc/ntp.conf&lt;/code&gt;.  As I had found issues with the default configuration, I needed to learn
more about this configuration file to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the file using a command like &lt;code&gt;more /etc/ntp.conf&lt;/code&gt; was daunting.  There were a
number of 1-2 line sections with multiple lines of comments before them.  When I saw that,
I was concerned.  In my experience, a large comment to useful line ratio means they are
commenting the heck out of it, because people have done stupid things in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning more about the configuration, it turned out that I only needed to look at one
particular section.  The most important part of the configuration is a section that started
with the follow text:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# pool.ntp.org maps to about 1000 low-stratum NTP servers.  Your server will
# pick a different set every time it starts up.  Please consider joining the
# pool: &amp;lt;http://www.pool.ntp.org/join.html&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right after this text, there was a group of servers specified where the first part of the
server name was a number between 0 and 3, and the rest of the server name was the same.  Many
of the articles I found didn’t touch the rest of the file, but focused on that small set of
lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very useful page I found during my research was the
&lt;a href="http://support.ntp.org/bin/view/Servers/NTPPoolServers"&gt;NTP Pool Time Servers&lt;/a&gt;
page.  Near the bottom of that page is a table that lists the various geographic areas,
from which I selected the &lt;code&gt;North America&lt;/code&gt; selection.  At the top of the next page was a
clearly marked section of text, with clear instruction to add that text to the &lt;code&gt;ntp.conf&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that information, I went back to the Raspbian machine, entered &lt;code&gt;sudo nano /etc/ntp.conf&lt;/code&gt;
to edit the &lt;code&gt;/etc/ntp.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, and replaced the default &lt;code&gt;debian&lt;/code&gt; servers in that section
with the information from the clearly marked section of the NTP Pool Time Servers page.
Followed up with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-X&lt;/code&gt; to save, &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; to save the file, &lt;code&gt;enter&lt;/code&gt; to use the provided file
name, and it was changed.   Just to make sure, I did another &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt; after verifying my
changes, and the &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt; command now returned the right date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2d-verify-that-the-ntp-service-is-working"&gt;Step 2d: Verify that the NTP Service is Working&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2d-verify-that-the-ntp-service-is-working" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a number of Denial-Of-Service attacks have used the NTP port to return bad information, a number of routers come pre-configured with their firewalls set to block port 123, the NTP port.  If you follow these instructions and are still having issues, check the firewall settings for your computer and your router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, when I had checked the status of the NTP service using the &lt;code&gt;ntpq -p&lt;/code&gt; command,
I did not seeing anything other than &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; in the when column of the output.  If things were
working properly, I would expect that column to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submitting the &lt;code&gt;ntpq -p&lt;/code&gt; command once the system rebooted, I got the following output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;     remote           refid      st t when poll reach   delay   offset  jitter
==============================================================================
-grom.polpo.org  127.67.113.92    2 u   21   64    1   59.302    9.614   6.053
+199.180.133.100 140.142.234.133  3 u   17   64    1   26.382    5.225   3.611
+time1-inapsales 216.218.254.202  2 u   17   64    1   41.043   -2.463   4.417
*vps5.ctyme.com  216.218.254.202  2 u   18   64    1   36.759   -5.673   2.870
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submitting the command multiple times, I observed the when column values increasing to
a certain point before starting over at a low single digit number.  From the documentation,
this was a good indication that each of those servers was being queried successfully, then
registering itself for the next time to check against that server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing the successful connections with the NTP servers, the time synchronization issues
were cleared up!  Just to be sure, I did a couple of cycles of &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt; and checking
the time, with no errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-accomplished"&gt;What Was Accomplished&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-was-accomplished" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article detailed the steps taken to fix two of the major issues I had after installing
Raspbian on my Raspberry Pi: the Wi-Fi access and the system clock being out of sync.  I worked
through the various steps taken to ensure that the wireless access was up and running,
including the various checks I did throughout the process.  I then walked through the steps
I took to ensure that the time on the Raspberry Pi was reflecting actual time, despite not
having an onboard system clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this accomplished, I had confidence in having firm foundations on which to start building
the display part of my glanceable display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next"&gt;What’s Next?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#whats-next" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next article in this series,
Glanceable Displays: Setting Up The Display
I walk through the steps I took to add the configuration to the Raspberry Pi to start the
display in the correct mode to use for the glanceable display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ellipses"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any of these examples, a set of ellipses (“…”) are used to denote that content was removed that was either sensitive or not relevant to the example being presented. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ellipses" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Glanceable Displays"></category></entry><entry><title>Glanceable Displays: Installing Raspbian on a Raspberry Pi</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-07-21:/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methods detailed …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methods detailed in this article provide for simple installation of the Raspbian
operating system using the
&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/installation/noobs.md"&gt;New Out Of Box Software (NOOBS)&lt;/a&gt;
installation method, as suggested for beginners by the
&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org"&gt;Raspberry Pi site&lt;/a&gt;.  While there are more direct methods
for experienced users, the NOOBs installation was selected for it’s simplicity and ease of
installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the NOOBs installation, this article details the first steps I took in setting up one of
my Raspberry Pi systems to be a glanceable display for my family.  Those steps start with the
formatting of a MicroSD card and installation of the NOOBs installer on to that MicroSD card.
After installing that card into the Raspberry Pi, the steps continue with the installation
of a stock Raspbian distribution, detailing the a couple of questions that need to be answered
to complete the installation.  Finally, to enable remote access, the last step is to ensure
that I can access the Raspberry Pi using SSH for later configuration and control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="requirements"&gt;Requirements&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#requirements" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi, version 3.0 or later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Supply for Raspberry Pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyboard and Mouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HDMI cable connected to monitor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cat5 Ethernet cable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please keep your own notes as you go, and refer back to them.  While I have tested the steps on my own Raspberry Pi machines, they were by no means exhaustive tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-1-interfacing-with-a-microsd-card"&gt;Step 1: Interfacing With a MicroSD Card&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-1-interfacing-with-a-microsd-card" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration and main drive for a Raspberry Pi is a MicroSD card.  To get the card
ready for use, your computer must be able to interface with the card.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most computers do not come with MicroSD slots, but there are a fair number with SD slots.&lt;br/&gt;
To make things easier for MicroSD buyers, some of the more high
end MicroSD makers include a MicroSD-to-SD adapter in their packaging, such as
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B06XWN9Q99"&gt;this 32GB MicroSD card from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.  I started
out using this, but found that the adapter was only good for 3-4 uses, not for continual use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative is a more multi-purpose adaptor, such as
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01KFXS83W"&gt;this multi-adapter from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.  As it is
made from a more durable material, it will survive more uses.  The one that I bought from
Amazon at 7.00 USD is still working after about 70+ uses, so at 0.10 USD per use, it has
already paid for itself.  Also, as it has a USB adapter, I can plug it into a USB extension
cable that I already have on my desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever way you decide to go, make sure to add the MicroSD card to the adapter before
plugging the adaptor into you computer.  Once it is securely in the adapter, make sure to
apply it to the relevant slot on your computer firmly, and make sure the connection is there.
On my Windows 10 machine, I can tell this happens as it will acknowledge the connection by
opening up an Explorer window, with either a “please format” instruction or a list of any
files in the directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-2-getting-the-microsd-card-ready"&gt;Step 2: Getting the MicroSD Card Ready&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2-getting-the-microsd-card-ready" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the steps that follow are for my Windows 10 machine.  The
&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/installation/noobs.md"&gt;NOOBs site&lt;/a&gt;, has sections for installing on Mac and Linux, but I did not test them.  If they do not work,please Google/Bing &lt;code&gt;linux microsd card format&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;linux microsd card mount&lt;/code&gt;. Feel free to replace the generic &lt;code&gt;linux&lt;/code&gt; in the searches with the name of the Linux distribution that you are using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2a-reformatting-a-used-microsd-card"&gt;Step 2a: Reformatting a Used MicroSD Card&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2a-reformatting-a-used-microsd-card" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reusing old hardware is important, for many reasons such as the environment and cost. To make
sure that is possible, it took me a number of tries to create a solid recipe for reformatting
the MicroSD cards.  As I mention in the &lt;code&gt;Requirements&lt;/code&gt; section, keep good notes of what you
do, or if following a recipe like this one, what changes you made to the recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a command line only tool that will also do the job, I found it clunky and hard
to use.  Instead, the Disk Management applet for the control panel was the tool I settled on.
This can be invoked by typing &lt;code&gt;partition&lt;/code&gt; in the search window on the tool bar and selecting
the &lt;code&gt;create and format hard disk partitions&lt;/code&gt; item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selecting that item brought up the &lt;code&gt;Disk Management&lt;/code&gt; window, showing a break down of
every drive connected to my computer.  When the MicroSD card was properly connected to the
computer, it showed up as Removable media after all of my permanent drives.  Using the right
mouse button, I clicked on each of the blocks on my MicroSD card and selected the
&lt;code&gt;Delete Volume&lt;/code&gt; menu item until all of the volumes were gone.  When that was accomplished, I
was left with two blocks, and right clicking on the rightmost block presented me with a
&lt;code&gt;Delete Partition&lt;/code&gt; menu item, which consolidated all of the partitions into a single
unallocated block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, I was able to right click on the Unallocated partition to select the
&lt;code&gt;Create Volume&lt;/code&gt; menu item.  This started a simple wizard that quickly walked me through
the options for creating a new volume.  I used all defaults that were presented with the
exception of the &lt;code&gt;file system&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;quick format&lt;/code&gt; settings.  I changed the &lt;code&gt;file system&lt;/code&gt;
setting to &lt;code&gt;FAT32&lt;/code&gt; and unchecked the &lt;code&gt;Use Quick Format&lt;/code&gt; checkbox, before clicking on
finish and waiting for about 30 minutes before the format was complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2b-formatting-a-new-microsd-card"&gt;Step 2b: Formatting a New MicroSD Card&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-2b-formatting-a-new-microsd-card" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a Windows 10 point of view, this was easy.  When the MicroSD card was properly connected
to my computer, it prompted me to format the card, presenting me with the format dialog
itself.  When formatting the MicroSD card, it was important to select &lt;code&gt;FAT32&lt;/code&gt; as the type
of format and to unselect &lt;code&gt;Quick Format&lt;/code&gt; on the dialog.  Once I clicked the format button,
it took a good while before it was completed.  As a rough estimate, I guessed that it was
roughly 1 minute per gigabyte on the MicroSD card, regardless of computer speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-3-install-raspbian-lite-using-noobs"&gt;Step 3: Install Raspbian Lite Using NOOBS&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-3-install-raspbian-lite-using-noobs" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the format is finished from the previous step, it is important to go to your taskbar and eject the media from your computer.  I accomplished this by right clicking on the USB stick icon and selecting “Eject Mass Storage Device” from the menu.  At that point, I cleanly removed the adaptor and the MicroSD card from the computer to ensure the ejection was complete. When I tested various scenarios, any time that I forgot to eject the media at this point, it did not take later on.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people behind the Raspberry PI made sure there is a simple to use installation system
that simplifies the task of installing operating systems on to the Raspberry Pi.  The
&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/installation/noobs.md"&gt;New Out Of Box Software (NOOBS)&lt;/a&gt;
site aims to allow a fairly basic installation of Raspberry Pi operating systems with
little effort.  Unless you are familiar with Linux systems, their installation can be
very daunting, so it is best to keep the installation as simple as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start that process, I downloaded the
&lt;a href="https://downloads.raspberrypi.org/NOOBS_latest"&gt;NOOBS zip file&lt;/a&gt; from their web site
to my computer.  After reinserting the MicroSD card and adapter to my computer, I then unzipped
the contents of the &lt;code&gt;NOOBS_V3_2_0.zip&lt;/code&gt; file to the root of the drive for the MicroSD card.
I had to take care to ensure that the contents were in the root of the drive, not in a
subdirectory of the drive.  This happened enough times that I actually unzipped the files to
a local directory and just used XCOPY to copy the files over, solving the placement problem
for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the note at the start of this section, once this action was done, I once again ejected
the USB device before disconnecting it from the computer, for the same reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the MicroSD card, I found the MicroSD port on the Raspberry Pi.  The port is flat with
the motherboard of the Raspberry Pi, and the cases I have all have a hole in the case to
make it easy to find.  Inserting the card into the port, I then attached the other cables for
monitor (HDMI), ethernet (Cat5), keyboard (USB), and mouse (USB), with the 5V adapter cable
being last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two minutes later, I was presented with a screen which prompted me to select the operating
system to install.  I tried a number of times to get the &lt;code&gt;Raspbian Lite&lt;/code&gt; install to work, but
encountered a number of issues, so I defaulted to the stock &lt;code&gt;Raspbian [RECOMMENDED]&lt;/code&gt; install.
Once I made this choice, I selected &lt;code&gt;Raspbian [RECOMMENDED]&lt;/code&gt; from the top of the list in the
NOOBs installation dialog, followed by pressing the &lt;code&gt;Install&lt;/code&gt; button at the top.  From there,
it took about 30 minutes or so before I was prompted with a dialog box that said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;OS(es) installed successfully
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I pressed the &lt;code&gt;OK&lt;/code&gt; button on that dialog, the system rebooted with first a rainbow
screen, then a screen with a big raspberry on it, then lots of text scrolling by quickly.
After a relatively small amount of action and a lot of waiting, it was now time to set up
the operating system for simple uses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-4-initial-system-setup"&gt;Step 4: Initial System Setup&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-4-initial-system-setup" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of text that scrolled by so quickly, I was unable to read it.  From what
I could see, there were a lot of green OK texts on the left side, so I guessed that the
installation had succeeded.  After a nice round of blinking lights from the Raspberry Pi,
the desktop showed up and proceeded to walk me through the setup configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first dialog was pretty simple, with the title &lt;code&gt;Welcome to Raspberry Pi&lt;/code&gt;.  The important
thing to note off of this dialog is at the bottom right of the dialog is the IP address that
the system currently has assigned to it.  As this was important, I wrote it down, and
proceeded with the rest of the configuration.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration is a series of simple dialogs, each giving a clear indication of what is
required.  Whenever I pressed the &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt; button, it wrote the information to the system
configuration files.  As such, I expect delays between when I pressed the &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt; button and
when the next dialog showed up.  Turns out that was a rather healthy expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the things that were setup were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time zone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setting a new password&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take care of black border&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;update software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having tested this workflow, I knew that the next workflow for my glanceable display would
include updating existing packages and installing new packages.  As such, I skipped the
update software, knowing I would do it later.  Both paths produce the same results, so feel
free to skip it like I did, or update at a later point.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you forget the password that you change it to, there is no easy way to recover what you changed the password to.  Consider creating a &lt;em&gt;fake&lt;/em&gt; entry in a password manager, like LastPass, and storing the password there for later use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-5-setting-up-ssh-access"&gt;Step 5: Setting Up SSH Access&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#step-5-setting-up-ssh-access" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being accomplished, the last thing to complete before stopping the installation of the
bare bones system was to enable SSH access. By enabling SSH access, I could sit at my
comfortable workspace, using my normal computer, chair, and desk instead of at the workbench
where I had the Raspberry Pi connected.  Frankly, the computer was connected in an almost
Frankenstein like mess of wires on an old desk with a chair that was normally reserved for
people visiting, not typing. My own workspace looked very inviting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable access, I entered the command &lt;code&gt;sudo raspi-config&lt;/code&gt;, selecting
&lt;code&gt;5. Interfacing Options&lt;/code&gt;, then selecting &lt;code&gt;P2 SSH&lt;/code&gt;, and finally answering Yes to the question
&lt;code&gt;Would you like the SSH server to be enabled?&lt;/code&gt;.  After this, the computer took about 30
seconds before being responsive again, with the text &lt;code&gt;The SSH server is enabled.&lt;/code&gt; appearing
on the screen.  Pressing the enter key, and then selecting &lt;code&gt;Finish&lt;/code&gt;, I was then back at the
command prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the moment I was working towards: being able to have a bare bones system to use that
I could access from my own computer.  Entering &lt;code&gt;sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt;, I waited about 45 seconds for
the system to reboot and to be greeted with the &lt;code&gt;raspberrypi login:&lt;/code&gt; prompt.  Looking just
above that text, I saw the text:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;[ OK ] Started OpenBSD Secure Shell server.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gave me a bit of confidence to move forward.  At the very least, the operating system
was indicating that it should allow SSH access.  At the command line, I entered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ssh pi@192.168.2.3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and with the exception of the input &lt;code&gt;yes&lt;/code&gt; to answer the question, the output was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The authenticity of host '192.168.2.3 (192.168.2.3)' can't be established.
ECDSA key fingerprint is SHA256:`some text here`.
Are you sure you want to continue connecting (yes/no)? yes
Warning: Permanently added '192.168.2.3' (ECDSA) to the list of known hosts.
...
pi@raspberrypi:~ $
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After each repeated installation on the same Raspberry Pi, when I went back to open a new SSH connection, it would report the error &lt;code&gt;WARNING: REMOTE HOST IDENTIFICATION HAS CHANGED!&lt;/code&gt;.  To allow access, I needed to edit the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/known_hosts&lt;/code&gt; file and remove the line for the IP address of the machine, as indicated at the end of the provided error message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-accomplished"&gt;What Was Accomplished&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-was-accomplished" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article detailed the steps taken to install the Raspbian operating system on a MicroSD
card.  It started by my formatting of the MicroSD card and copying the NOOBs installer onto
the card, followed by inserting it into the Raspberry Pi’s MicroSD slot.  The steps continued
with the largely automated installation of the operating system, only requiring the answers
to six questions on my part.  Finally, it concluded with the setup for SSH to allow me to
configure the Raspberry Pi remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next"&gt;What’s Next?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#whats-next" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next article in this series,
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/28/glanceable-displays-fine-tuning-a-raspberry-pi-installation/"&gt;Glanceable Displays: Fine Tuning A Raspberry Pi Installation&lt;/a&gt;,
I walk through the steps I took to move the installation from a bare bones system, to one that
had Wi-Fi and time support set up properly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Glanceable Displays"></category></entry><entry><title>Glanceable Displays: What Are They?</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/14/glanceable-displays-what-are-they/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-07-14:/2019/07/14/glanceable-displays-what-are-they/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="preface"&gt;Preface&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#preface" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first article in a series about Glanceable Displays and my efforts to create
one for my household.  For other articles in the series, click on the title of the article
under the heading “Glanceable Displays” on the right side of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will introduce the concept of glanceable displays and describe how they can
be used in an everyday office or home.  I will then discuss how the audience for the
display is important, including a side bar about my opinion on Spousal Acceptance Factor.
Understanding the limitations of your audience is also covered, leading up to developing a set
of definitions on what should be displayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will talk about how my family followed those steps to arrive at the requirements
for our glanceable display, which has buy in from every member of our household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-glanceable-displays"&gt;What Are Glanceable Displays?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-are-glanceable-displays" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/glanceable"&gt;Dictionary.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 noting or relating to information on an electronic screen that can be understood quickly or at a glance:
glanceable data;
a glanceable scoreboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 enabling information on a screen to be quickly understood:
a glanceable design;
glanceable interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, a glanceable display is a display that provides information that can be quickly
understood by people reading the display.  An important qualification of these displays is
that the information they display needs to have a broad degree of applicability without any
ability for a specific reader to customize the data to their needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the display must provide information with no personal customization, it is important to
think about various things up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-is-the-display-for"&gt;Who Is the Display For?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#who-is-the-display-for" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience of the display will drive many of the other choices for the glanceable
display.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be honest about who the real audience is for your glanceable display, and what benefits that
audience will gain from the display.   Negotiate with the audience members and make sure that
there is something on the display for each member.  If possible, engage with those members to
help with the display so their work becomes part of the display, fostering interest from the
beginning.  The key is for your project to make the jump from “my toy project” to
“our useful project”, solving real world issues with real world requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not honest about your audience and communicated with them sincerely, you will
invariably end up missing your goals for the display.   Without these, your base requirements
will not be correct, and your final product will not be correct.  If you only want
the display for your personal office, it is perfectly acceptable for you to say that you are
the sole audience and geek out on the display.  That is, it is acceptable if you are honest
about that audience.  In that case, just be realistic and don’t expect people you didn’t
include in your original audience to appreciate your display.  After all, you made it just for
you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="spousal-acceptance-factor"&gt;Spousal Acceptance Factor&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#spousal-acceptance-factor" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, I have often heard of concerns from people about something they made having a
low SAF or Spousal Acceptance Factor.  I honestly think that is silly.  If there is a low SAF,
it probably means that someone did something where their spouse was either not consulted on not
considered in terms of requirements.  It is human to want to share your excitement with family
around you but remember that your excitement is not their excitement.  Unless you sincerely
include them in the audience, the chance of acceptance will remain low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-are-you-going-to-display-it"&gt;How Are You Going To Display It?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#how-are-you-going-to-display-it" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of deciding how to display the glanceable information, we really have only one
decision to make: are we going to ask the viewer to visit an online site with a device or are
we going to provide access to a device at a given location?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide on the visit paradigm, you don’t have any hardware concerns as the reader is
supplying the hardware.  With the viewer using their own device to view the display, another
decision must be made regarding whether to standardize on a single device type or to support
multiple device types.  If you decide to support multiple device types, you will probably need
to use an intermediate step where you start with support for only the most used device type.
Once that device type has been completed, you can then slowly adapt your display to the next
device type your viewers are using.  You will also need to ensure that you have a clear
definition on where your display can be accessed from.  If you have a web site for your
office that you display on phones or tablets, can it be viewed from anywhere, or just
within the office’s WiFi area?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide on the specific location paradigm, you limit your device type to one, but you
take on additional hardware concerns.  You get to focus on a single device type, but in
exchange, you need to provide for the setup and control of that device.  Consider the case
where the power goes off and then comes back.  How will your hardware solution handle that or
will someone need to reboot it?  Another important consideration is the cost of the hardware
and any needed peripherals.  Will you reuse existing hardware that you already have, or will
you require expenditures?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output from your evaluation of this section should be a choice of a single approach and a
list of reasons why the selected approach was chosen.  If possible, provide as many details as
possible as it will help you in other sections going forward.  Also, from your audience’s
point of view, it will help them understand the decisions that you have asked them to buy in
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-do-you-need-to-consider-up-front"&gt;What Do You Need To Consider Up Front?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-do-you-need-to-consider-up-front" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the display is a glanceable display, this means that everyone should be able to view the
display with few issues, if any.  Common issues to think about are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="near-and-far-sightedness"&gt;Near and Far Sightedness&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#near-and-far-sightedness" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large segment of every population either wears glasses or contacts at some point in their
life.  Especially as people get older, their eyesight gets weaker and they rely on glasses
more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the differing eyesight of your audience, you may want to consider using
larger fonts to enable them to see the screen more clearly.  In addition, you may want to
consider a high contract mode that includes fewer, but bolder colors to improve visibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="color-blindness"&gt;Color Blindness&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#color-blindness" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Color blindness, as shown in this article
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_blindness"&gt;on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
is an inability to see differences in either all colors or certain types of colors.  Keep in
mind that if you audience is not a family environment, the person with color blindness may not
disclose that they are color blind up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one of your audience is color blind, using colors on your display to indicate certain
things is a bad idea.  Use shapes or text instead of colors to denote differences in the
data being displayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dyslexia-and-other-reading-disorders"&gt;Dyslexia and Other Reading Disorders&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#dyslexia-and-other-reading-disorders" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyslexia, as shown in this article &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyslexia"&gt;on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, is
actually a family of similar disorders involving the brain and how numbers and letters are
processed when reading.  Other reading disorders, such as those mentioned in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reading_disability"&gt;this Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;, are often grouped
by people as dyslexia, when they are only related.  As with dyslexia, keep in
mind that if you audience is not a family environment, the person with dyslexia may not
disclose that they are color blind up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advances in research on reading issues have produced advances such as the
&lt;a href="https://www.dyslexiefont.com/en/typeface/"&gt;Dyslexie font&lt;/a&gt; which is specially made for people
with dyslexia.  Engage with your audience to determine if any such issues apply, what their
effects are, and talk with them and research with them on ways to adapt the display to make
it easier for them to comprehend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="young-readers"&gt;Young Readers&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#young-readers" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young readers, due to their age, are either still learning how to read or are building their
vocabulary as the grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assist any young readers that are going to use your display, consider replacing some of
the objects that you want to display with pictures that indicate the object’s meaning.  For
‘older’ young readers, keep in mind that their vocabulary is different than yours, and change
you designs for the display accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-you-going-to-display"&gt;What Are You Going To Display?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-are-you-going-to-display" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have all the other sections taken care of, the decision of what to put on the
display is almost anti-climactic.  After going through the process of identifying your
audience, the type of display to use, and any considerations for your audience, you have
probably defined at least one or two things to display along the way.  At the very least,
armed with the information above, you can engage with your audience in a brainstorming session
that will allow you to get buy-in from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important things to remember at this stage: soliciting help and iterative development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to ask your audience to help you in the design for the display.  That can
take any form you want, from design the information for the display with them there to asking
them to create the displays and presenting them to the entire audience.  Remember, for the
glanceable display to be successful, you will need buy-in from your audience.  Having them
help with the work will do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iterative development means that you and your audience are going to try and make something
that works, but you do not expect it to be perfect on the first try.  You and your audience may
be confident think something works when you look at it initially, but over time that
confidence may change.  Don’t be afraid to iterate on the design, keeping the things that work
and changing the things that don’t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="our-discussion-about-our-glanceable-display"&gt;Our Discussion About Our Glanceable Display&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#our-discussion-about-our-glanceable-display" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding that any decision would affect my entire family, I asked if we could talk
about it after dinner one night.  In discussing the possibility of a display, we all agreed
that there were common things that it would be nice to see.  These things came down to 3
categories: calendar related, weather related, and other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we all have busy lives, the calendar was a slam dunk.  Our whiteboard calendar didn’t get
updated when it should, which left us looking at our online calendars on our phones.  But even
with our online calendars, it was a pain to remember to invite other family members to any
events we had, regardless of whether or not they were part of the event.  Having a single place
to display that information keyed to a given individual would clear things up and simplify
things a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information on the weather was another category, mostly due to the Seattle weather.  While my
son wears the same type of clothes every day, my wife and I vary our clothing by the type of
weather and activities we have planned.  Having that advance knowledge of weather would cut
down on having to actively seek that information from a number of online sources.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After those two big categories, there were also some other little things brought up.  Not
having a good place to put them, the “others” category was formed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion then moved to decide which class of glanceable display to use, and our family
made a simple decision to go with a monitor driven by a web page hosted on a Raspberry Pi.  We
all agreed that we wanted something that would replace a seldom updated whiteboard calendar in
our kitchen.  It needed to be big enough to show several weeks’ worth of calendar at a time, to
allow us to plan that far out.  We also wanted to make sure we kept each other honest, so we
explicitly wanted it not tied to any of our personal computers and tied to a location that we
know we all frequent: the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice of the Raspberry Pi satisfied these concerns pretty easily.  From a hardware point
of view, I had a spare one at home from a project I had wanted to do, but never started.  From
an operating system point of view, I have enough knowledge of Linux systems that I was
confident that I would be able to handle the configuration.  Finally, I was prepared to take
the challenge on of setting up the system and working with my family to define the elements
of the display with their input at ever step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-decisions-for-our-glanceable-display"&gt;The Decisions for Our Glanceable Display&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#the-decisions-for-our-glanceable-display" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, from those discussions, I arrived at the following.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="audience"&gt;Audience&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#audience" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience was our family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="display"&gt;Display&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#display" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The display itself would be a simple Raspberry Pi with a monitor that was left from a project
that I had (almost) worked on.  The display would be located in the kitchen in a location that
would be visible to family members, but not visible outside of the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="considerations"&gt;Considerations&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#considerations" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our family, we don’t have any members that have vision issues other than needing glasses.
As such, the primary concern is that we can all ready the text on the display from 2 meters or
6 feet away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-to-display"&gt;What To Display?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-to-display" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary two goals for the display were to display our calendars and the weather for the
next 5 days.  Any enhancements of those two goals were fine, as long as the primary goals
were not ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the other ideas that were floated may seem funny, but they nicely fit into our other
category:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chore lists from Trello&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quote of the day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of days until Christmas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of people on the International Space Station&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;current exchange rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrapping-it-up"&gt;Wrapping It Up&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#wrapping-it-up" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the articles in this series will detail my family and I worked on our
glanceable display.  Based on the information from above, we have had good success with
our display. Most of the fixes to the display were tweaks to the information being displayed,
rather than the Raspberry Pi itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I emphatically stand by the previous sections about and making sure you understand and engage
your audience.  I credit my family, the audience for our glanceable display, with having an
honest conversation on what would help, and getting the buy in from them from the beginning.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-accomplished"&gt;What Was Accomplished?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-was-accomplished" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presented a set of things to consider when creating a glanceable display,
followed by notes on how my family followed that pattern to arrive at our requirements
for our glanceable display.  Those considerations started with defining your audience,
proceeded to understanding your audience, and finally arriving at a set of things that
you and your audience want to display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot promise that if you follow these considerations that your journey will be as
successful as ours.  However, I believe I can say with some certainty that it will help you
along the way with your own journey.  To succeed, you need information to help guide you, and
each of the considerations above will help you inch closer to that success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next"&gt;What’s Next?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#whats-next" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next article in this series,
&lt;a href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/21/glanceable-displays-installing-raspbian-on-a-raspberry-pi/"&gt;Glanceable Displays: Installing Raspbian on a Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt;,
I walk through the steps I took to set up a Raspberry Pi as our glanceable display of choice.
It documents the journey from installation on to a blank MicroSD card to a bare bones
installation that enabled remote SSH access.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="glanceable"></category><category term="glanceable displays"></category></entry><entry><title>Starting With GitHub: Setting Up Credentials For My Personal Website</title><link href="https://jackdewinter.github.io/2019/07/07/starting-with-github-setting-up-credentials-for-my-personal-website/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jack De Winter</name></author><id>tag:jackdewinter.github.io,2019-07-07:/2019/07/07/starting-with-github-setting-up-credentials-for-my-personal-website/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In setting up this website, I needed to make sure I had Git&lt;sup id="fnref:Git"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:Git"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and more specifically
GitHub &lt;sup id="fnref:GitHub"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:GitHub"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; setup to use the GitHub Pages&lt;sup id="fnref:GitHubPages"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:GitHubPages"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; feature.  My source
control tool of choice was already Git, so it made sense to make my website platform of
choice GitHub Pages …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In setting up this website, I needed to make sure I had Git&lt;sup id="fnref:Git"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:Git"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and more specifically
GitHub &lt;sup id="fnref:GitHub"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:GitHub"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; setup to use the GitHub Pages&lt;sup id="fnref:GitHubPages"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:GitHubPages"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; feature.  My source
control tool of choice was already Git, so it made sense to make my website platform of
choice GitHub Pages&lt;sup id="fnref2:GitHubPages"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:GitHubPages"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  I made this choice to ensure that I can write articles
with little or no changes to my normal workflow.  Part of any project I do, private or
open-source, is setting up a version control system and securing access to that version
control system.  It is always a high priority for me to make sure that any Git access is
secure and follows best common practices on security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article details the actions and choices I made in setting up my access to GitHub for my
blog.  It details how I followed the GitHub Pages instructions for creating a personal website
and creating a personal repository on GitHub to achieve that.  Then it describes the two modes
of accessing GitHub, SSH and HTTPS, and why I chose SSH.  Finally, it provides detailed notes
on how I generated a SSH keypair specifically for GitHub, and configured both my local Git and
the remote GitHub to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="getting-started-with-github"&gt;Getting Started With GitHub&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#getting-started-with-github" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many good articles out there on how to install Git for different operating systems,
so I&amp;rsquo;ll assume any readers following along can do the research needed to install Git for their
system.  Setting up access to GitHub is even easier as the folks at GitHub have provided
excellent instructions.  Simply go to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;GitHub Home Page&lt;/a&gt; and it will
either allow you to login if you have an account, or create a new account if you don&amp;rsquo;t.  As I
had already dealt with a couple of open source projects, I already have an account
&lt;code&gt;jackdewinter&lt;/code&gt;, so I logged in without any issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I logged in, the browser deposited me on my home page.  From there I was able to see
any projects that I had either contributed to or filed an issue against.  Just starting in my
Open Source journey, the contents were only a couple of projects that I had filed issues with.
Prior to this point, I had no need to authenticate my Git client with GitHub as I was just
downloading from public repositories.  I figured out quickly that setting up my own website
would require my own repositories, so I determined that authentication would also be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="creating-my-first-github-repository"&gt;Creating My First GitHub Repository&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#creating-my-first-github-repository" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages home page&lt;/a&gt; has a really simple formula on their
webpage for setting up personal webpages.  Step 1 was pretty easy: I made sure that
that the name of the repository was my GitHub user id (in my case &lt;code&gt;jackdewinter&lt;/code&gt;) followed by
&lt;code&gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.  When the creation of my repository finished, GitHub deposited my browser
at the base of my new repository: &lt;code&gt;jackdewinter/jackdewinter.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining steps in the formula dealt with cloning the repository, defining a sample
&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file for my website, and pushing that code back to the repository.  While I was
familiar with those concepts, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t afraid to check back with the
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Getting-a-Git-Repository"&gt;Git Basics documentation&lt;/a&gt;
on the Git website when I forgot something.  From there I can usually find the correct helper
article on what I need to accomplish within 2-3 clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new concept that I had to deal with on the GitHub site is that unlike before, I was now
accessing a repository that was privately owned that I wanted to write to.  Unless you mark a
repository as private, everyone can see that repository and read from that repository.  My
website&amp;rsquo;s repository is public, so reading wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushing the code back to my repository would be writing, and was a problem.  Each project
has a list of who can write to it and the creator of the project is on that list by default.
But to write to the project, I had to have my local Git tool login to GitHub when needed and
authenticate.  I was going to have to dive into credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="github-authentication-ssh-vs-https"&gt;GitHub Authentication: SSH vs HTTPS&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#github-authentication-ssh-vs-https" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time you log in to a website or to a program by using your user id and password, you
establish your credentials.  You tell the website or program &amp;ldquo;I can prove I am me, let me see
my stuff!&amp;rdquo;.  The GitHub website is no different that any of those sites.  If you want to be
able to see any of your private stuff or write to your stuff, it needs to verify who you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to the &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/set-up-git#next-steps-authenticating-with-github-from-git"&gt;GitHub Authenticating Page&lt;/a&gt;,
there are two choices that allow us to connect to GitHub: HTTPS and SSH.  Both of these are
valid options, allowing for enhanced security when having Git connect to GitHub.  However,
each of these options has different things going for and against it.  After doing some
research, it seemed to me to break down to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSH&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HTTPS&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;set up keys&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;set up credential manager&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;setup is more involved&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;easy setup&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;less likely blocked by firewall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this information, I decided to go with SSH as I wanted to opt for more security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ssh-access-to-github"&gt;SSH Access to GitHub&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#ssh-access-to-github" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my research at the GitHub site, I had found this very good page on
&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/using-ssh-over-the-https-port"&gt;SSH over the HTTPS port&lt;/a&gt;.
In it, they explain that there is a simple test to see if SSH will work from your system to
GitHub.  When you execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ssh -T git@github.com
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;it will either return one of two responses.  If it returns with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; Hi *username*! You&amp;#39;ve successfully authenticated, but GitHub does not provide shell access.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;then you can access GitHub via SSH without any issues.  If you see the other response:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; ssh: connect to host github.com port 22: Connection timed out
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;then you have to setup SSH to connect to GitHub over the HTTPS port.  This access can be
verified with a small modification to the above command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ssh -T -p 443 git@ssh.github.com
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The command is now trying to establish a SSH session over port 443, and if you get the
&lt;code&gt;You've successfully&lt;/code&gt; response, it&amp;rsquo;s working fine.  Running these tests myself, I found
that I got a timeout on the first command and a success on the second command.  Following
the article, it recommends changes &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt;[^SSH_CONFIG] to include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary system is a Windows 10 machine, so instead of modifying the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file, I modified the &lt;code&gt;%HOMEDRIVE%%HOMEPATH%\.ssh\config&lt;/code&gt; file.  On my system, that file is the &lt;code&gt;c:\Users\jackd\.ssh\config&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Host github.com
  Hostname ssh.github.com
  Port 443
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next time, when I executed the &lt;code&gt;ssh -T git@github.com&lt;/code&gt; command, the response was
the &lt;code&gt;You've successfully&lt;/code&gt; response.  Now I was ready to set up the SSH keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unique-ssh-keys"&gt;Unique SSH Keys&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#unique-ssh-keys" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/set-up-git#next-steps-authenticating-with-github-from-git"&gt;GitHub Authenticating Page&lt;/a&gt;,
the next step was to generate a new SSH key pair and add it to my local SSH keyring.  The page
that points to &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent"&gt;generating a new key&lt;/a&gt;
is pretty detailed, so I won&amp;rsquo;t try and improve over GitHub&amp;rsquo;s work.  On my reading of the page,
it seems to assume that if you will only have 1 key pair&lt;sup id="fnref:keypair"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:keypair"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; generated and that you will
reuse that key pair for GitHub.  I have issues with that practice, so I want to talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a bit of a security background from my day job, I want to limit exposure if something
gets broken.  Just from a quick search, there are articles by
&lt;a href="https://askleo.com/why-is-it-so-important-to-use-a-different-password-on-every-site/"&gt;Leo Notenboom&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://blog.malwarebytes.com/101/2017/05/dont-need-27-different-passwords/"&gt;Malware Bytes Labs&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-Many-Different-Passwords-for-Many-Different-Websites"&gt;WikiHow&lt;/a&gt;
that all describe how you should have different passwords for each account, and in many cases,
use a password manager.  And to be honest, that was just the first 3 that I clicked on.  There
were a lot more.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can sum up and paraphrase the justification raised in each of those articles by posing a
single question: If someone breaks your password on one site, what is your exposure?  If you
have one password for all sites, then whoever breaks your password has access to that one
site.  If you have a different password for each site, the damage is limited to one site,
instead of all sites using that password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, using a key pair for credentials is a similar concept to using a user-id and
password for credentials.  Therefore, it followed that if I follow good security practices for
passwords, I should also follow the same practices for key pairs as credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="generating-a-new-key-for-github"&gt;Generating a New Key For GitHub&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#generating-a-new-key-for-github" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure I have secure access to GitHub, I followed the instructions
&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent"&gt;for generating a new key&lt;/a&gt;.
To generate a distinct key pair for GitHub, I made one small modification to the instructions:
I saved the new key pair information with the filename &lt;code&gt;github-key&lt;/code&gt; instead of the default
&lt;code&gt;id_ras&lt;/code&gt;.  This resulted in the files &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/github-key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/github-key.pub&lt;/code&gt;
being created as the key pair.  With those files created, I followed the remaining
instructions for setting up ssh-agent and uploading the key information to GitHub, replacing
any occurrence of &lt;code&gt;id_ras&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;github-key&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that accomplished, I had a specific key pair for GitHub and I had it registered locally.
I also had setup GitHub with the public portion of the credentials using the contents of
&lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/github-key.pub&lt;/code&gt;, as instructed.  The only remaining step was ensure that any SSH
connections to GitHub would use the GitHub credentials. Doing a bit more research on the SSH
configuration files, I quickly found that there was built in support for this by adding the
following to my &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Host github.com
  User git
  PreferredAuthentications publickey
  IdentityFile /c/Users/jackd/.ssh/github-key
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The location of &lt;code&gt;~/&lt;/code&gt; on my Windows machine is &lt;code&gt;%HOMEDRIVE%%HOMEPATH%\&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;c:\Users\jackd\&lt;/code&gt;.  The format for the &lt;code&gt;IdentityFile&lt;/code&gt; property is a standard Unix path format.  This requires a translation from the Windows path format &lt;code&gt;C:\Users\jackd\.ssh\github-key&lt;/code&gt; to the Unix path format of &lt;code&gt;/c/Users/jackd/.ssh/github-key&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with the change from earlier in this article, my &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file now looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Host github.com
  Hostname ssh.github.com
  Port 443
  User git
  PreferredAuthentications publickey
  IdentityFile /c/Users/jackd/.ssh/github-key
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I performed a number of thorough tests, and everything passed without any issues!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-accomplished"&gt;What Was Accomplished&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-was-accomplished" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article started with my creation of a GitHub repository to contain
the files for my personal website using GitHub Pages.  To securely access the repository, I
chose the SSH protocol and discovered that I needed to employ SSH over HTTP.  For enhanced
security, I described a solid reason for wanting a unique SSH key for GitHub.  Following that
advice, I generated a new key and then changed the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file to use SSH over HTTPS
and to point to that newly generated keypair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:Git"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git is an open-source source control tool.  For more information, &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/"&gt;look here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:Git" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:GitHub"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub is a common repository for open-source projects.  For more information, &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/set-up-git"&gt;look here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:GitHub" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:GitHubPages"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages are a feature of GitHub that allow people to host their personal websites on GitHub.  For more information, &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;look here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:GitHubPages" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:GitHubPages" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:keypair"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a SSH key is generated, it comes in two parts.  The private part is kept on the user&amp;rsquo;s system while the public part can be distributed to any interested parties.  Together they are referred to as a key pair.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:keypair" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="GitHub"></category></entry></feed>